<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A funeral sermon preached upon the death of the Reverend and Excellent Divine Dr. Thomas Manton, who deceas'd Octob. 18, 1677 by William Bates ... ; to which is now added, the last publick sermon Dr. Manton preached.</title>
            <author>Bates, William, 1625-1699.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1678</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 119 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 61 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A26793</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B1110</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R11400</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12536804</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12536804</idno>
            <idno type="VID">62862</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A26793)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 62862)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 304:25)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A funeral sermon preached upon the death of the Reverend and Excellent Divine Dr. Thomas Manton, who deceas'd Octob. 18, 1677 by William Bates ... ; to which is now added, the last publick sermon Dr. Manton preached.</title>
                  <author>Bates, William, 1625-1699.</author>
                  <author>Manton, Thomas, 1620-1677.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[5], 115, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by J.D. for Brabazon Aylmer ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1678.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Advertisements: p. [1] at end.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Manton, Thomas, 1620-1677.</term>
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Timothy, 2nd, I, 18 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Future life --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Funeral sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:62862:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:62862:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A Funeral Sermon, PREACHED Upon the Death of the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verend and Excellent Divine Dr. <hi>Thomas Manton,</hi> Who deceas'd <hi>Octob.</hi> 18. 1677.</p>
            <p>By <hi>William Bates,</hi> D. D.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>To which is now added,</hi> The Laſt Publick Sermon Dr. MANTON preached.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed by <hi>J. D.</hi> for <hi>Brabazon Aylmer,</hi> at the three Pigeons in <hi>Cornhil,</hi> over againſt the Royal Exchange. 1678.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:62862:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:62862:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>The Bookſeller to the READER.</head>
            <p>INtending to reprint this Funeral Sermon, it was judg'd convenient to annex to it, a Sermon of Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor <hi>Thomas Mantons,</hi> ſuitable to the Subject that was treated on, and being the laſt he publickly preached.</p>
            <p>This will ſhortly be followed with a Volumn of the Doctor's Sermons now in the Preſs.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:62862:3"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:62862:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>1</hi> Theſſ. <hi>4.17. the laſt clauſe.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>—And ſo ſhall we ever be with the Lord.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>THE Words are a Conſolation, brought by the Apoſtle from the <hi>third Heaven,</hi> where he was by extraordinary Privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge rais'd, and ſaw and underſtood how great an Happineſs it is to be with Chriſt. And they are addreſt to Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers, to moderate and allay their ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rows for the death of thoſe Saints, who by their conjunction in Blood or Friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip were moſt dear to them. Thus he ſpeaks in the 13th Verſe, <hi>I would not have you be ignorant, Brethren, concerning them which are aſleep, that yè ſorrow not as others which have no hopè.</hi> The Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens, that were ſtrangers to a future ſtate, and thought that after a ſhort courſe through the World, Mankind would be loſt for ever in the Dead-Sea,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:62862:4"/>might with ſome pretence abandon themſelves to the extremity of their Paſſions. But Chriſtians, to <hi>whom Life and Immortality are reveal'd by the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel; who believe, that as Jeſus died and roſe again; ſo all that ſleep in Jeſus, that perſevere</hi> in Faith and Holineſs to the end, <hi>God will bring with him,</hi> are forbid upon the moſt weighty Reaſons, to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulge their Grief in exceſs. The Union between Chriſt and Believers is invio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lable; and from thence it follows, they ſhall be partakers with him in his Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry. The Soul immediately after Death <hi>ſhall be with Chriſt.</hi> Whiles the Body re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſes in the Grave, 'tis in his Preſence who is Life and Light, and has a vital joyful Reſt in Communion with him. And in the appointed Time the Bodies of the Saints, thoſe happy Spoils, ſhall be reſcued from the dark Priſon of the Grave, and be ſharers with their Souls in immortal Glory.</p>
            <p>This conſummate Happineſs of the Saints, the Apoſtle aſſures from the higheſt Authority, <hi>the Word of the Lord;</hi>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:62862:4"/>and deſcribes his glorious Appearance, ſo as to make the ſtrongeſt Impreſſion on our Minds. <hi>For the Lord himſelf ſhall deſcend from Heaven with a Shout, with the Voice of an Arch-Angel, and with the Trump of God; and the Dead in Chriſt ſhall riſe firſt. Then we which are alive, and remain, ſhall be caught up toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with them in the Clouds, to meet the Lord in the Air; and ſo ſhall we ever be with the Lord.</hi> Then Death, the laſt Enemy, ſo fearful and feared by Men, ſhall be deſtroyed. And the Captive Prince of the World, with all the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of Darkneſs, and all other Rebelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Sinners that obſtinately joyn'd with him, ſhall be brought in Chains before his dreadful Tribunal: and after the great Act of the Univerſal Judgment ſhall be compleated, then all the Saints ſhall make their triumphant Entry with the Captain of their Salvation, into his Kingdom, and <hi>ſhall ever be with the Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The general Propoſition from the Words is this; <hi>The Saints after the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:62862:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>ſhall be Compleatly and Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally happy in the Preſence of Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To make this ſupernatural Bleſſedneſs more eaſie and intelligible to us, the Scripture deſcribes it by ſenſible Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſentations. For whilſt the Soul is cloath'd with Fleſh, Fancy has ſuch a dominion, that we can conceive of no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but by Compariſons and Images taken from material things. 'Tis there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſet forth by a Feaſt, and a <hi>King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom,</hi> to ſignifie the Joy and Glory of that State. But to prevent all groſs conceits; it tells us that the Bodies of the Saints ſhall be ſpiritual, not capable of Hunger and Thirſt, nor conſequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of any refreſhment that is cauſed by the ſatisfaction of thoſe appetites. The objects of the moſt noble ſenſes, Seeing and Hearing, the pleaſure of which is mix'd with Reaſon, and not common to the Brutes, are more frequently made uſe of to reconcile that glorious State to the proportion of our Minds. Thus ſometimes the Bleſſed are repreſented plac'd <hi>on Thrones with Crowns on their
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:62862:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>heads;</hi> ſometimes <hi>cloathed in White, with Palms in their hands;</hi> ſometimes ſing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Songs of triumph <hi>to Him that ſits on the Throne,</hi> and to their Saviour. But the reality of this Bleſſedneſs infinitely exceeds all thoſe faint Metaphors. Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven is leſſened by Compariſons from earthly things. The Apoſtle who was dignifi'd with the revelation of the ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſes that ſhall happen to the Church till Time ſhall be no more, tells us, <hi>it does not appear what we ſhall be in Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity. The things that God has prepar'd for thoſe that love him,</hi> are far more above the higeſt aſcent of our thoughts, than the Marriage-Feaſt of a great Prince exceeds in ſplendor and magni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficence the imagination of one that has always liv'd in an obſcure Village, and never ſaw any Ornaments of State, nor taſted Wine in his Life. We can think of thoſe things but according to the poverty of our Underſtandings. But ſo much we know that is able to ſwee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten all the bitterneſs, and render inſipid all the ſweetneſs of this World.</p>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:62862:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>This will appear by conſidering, that whatever is requiſite to conſtitute the perfect Bleſſedneſs of Man, is fully en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy'd in the Divine Preſence.</p>
            <p n="1">1. An exemption from all evils, is the firſt condition of perfect Bleſſed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs. The ſentence of wiſe <hi>Solon</hi> is true in another ſenſe than he intended,
<q>
                  <l>—Dicique beatus,</l>
                  <l>Ante obitum nemo, ſuprema<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> funera debet.</l>
               </q>No Man can be named happy whilſt in this valley of Tears. But upon the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trance into Heaven, all thoſe Evils that by their number, variety, or weight diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiet and oppreſs us, are at an end.</p>
            <p>Sin, of all evils the moſt hateful, ſhall be aboliſh'd. And all Temptations that ſurround us, and endanger our Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence, ſhall ceaſe. Here the beſt Men lament the weakneſs of the fleſh, and ſometimes the violent Aſſaults of Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual Enemies. St. <hi>Paul</hi> himſelf breaks forth into a mournful Complaint, <hi>O wretched man that I am! who ſhall deliver
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:62862:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>me from this body of Death?</hi> And when harraſs'd with the buffetings of Satan, renews his moſt earneſt Addreſſes to God to be freed from them. Here our Purity is not abſolute, we muſt be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways cleanſing our ſelves from the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licts of that deep defilement that cleaves to our nature. Here our Peace is pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerv'd with the Sword in our hand, by a continual Warfare againſt Satan and the World. But in Heaven no igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance darkens the Mind, no paſſions rebel againſt the ſanctified Will, no in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herent pollution remains. The Church is <hi>without ſpot or wrinkle, or any ſuch thing.</hi> And all Temptations <hi>that war againſt the Soul,</hi> ſhall then ceaſe. The Tempter was caſt out of Heaven, and none of his poiſon'd Arrows can reach that Purified Company. <hi>Glorious Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty!</hi> here ardently deſir'd, but fully enjoy'd by the Sons of God above.</p>
            <p>And as Sin, ſo all the penal conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quences of it are quite taken away. The preſent Life is an incurable Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe, and ſometimes attended with that
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:62862:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>ſharp ſenſe that Death is deſir'd as a Remedy, and accepted as a Benefit. And though the Saints have reviving Cordials, yet their joys are mixt with ſorrows, nay, cauſed by ſorrows. The tears of Repentance are their ſweeteſt refreſhment. Here the <hi>living ſtones</hi> are cut and wounded, and made fit by Sufferings for a Temple unto God in the <hi>New Jeruſalem.</hi> But as in the build<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of <hi>Solomon</hi>'s Temple the noiſe of a hammer was not heard, for all the parts were fram'd before with that exact de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign and correſpondence, that they firm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly combin'd together. They were hew'n in another place, and nothing remain'd but the putting them one up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on another in the Temple; and then, as ſacred, they were inviolable. So God, <hi>the wiſe Architect,</hi> having pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>par'd the Saints here by many cutting Afflictions, places them in the <hi>Eternal Building,</hi> where no voice of Sorrow is heard. Of the innumerable Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny above, is there any Eye that weeps, any Breaſt that ſighs, any Tongue that
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:62862:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>complains, or appearance of Grief? The Heavenly State is called <hi>Life,</hi> as only worthy of that title. There is no Infirmity of Body, no Poverty, no Diſgrace, no Treachery of Friends, no Perſecution of Enemies. <hi>There is no more Death, nor Sorrow, nor Crying, nor ſhall there be any more Pain: for former things are paſt away.</hi> (Rev. 21.4.) God <hi>will wipe away all tears from the eyes of his People.</hi> Their Salvation is compleat in all degrees. Pure Joy is the Privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg of Heaven, unmixed Sorrows the Puniſhment of Hell.</p>
            <p>A concurrence of all poſitive Excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lencies is requiſite to Bleſſedneſs. And theſe are to be conſidered with reſpect to the entire Man.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The Body ſhall be awak'd out of its dead ſleep, and quickned into a glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious, immortal Life. The Soul and Body are the eſſential parts of Man; and though the inequality be great in their operations that reſpect Holineſs, yet their concourſe is neceſſary. Good Actions are deſign'd by the Counſel
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:62862:8"/>and Reſolution of the Spirit, but per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form'd by the Miniſtry of the Fleſh. Every Grace expreſſes it ſelf in viſible Actions by the Body. In the ſorrows of Repentance it ſupplies Tears, in Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtings its Appetites are reſtrain'd, in Thankſgivings the Tongue breaks forth into the joyful praiſes of God. All the victories over ſenſible pleaſure and pain are obtain'd by the Soul in conjunction with the Body. Now 'tis moſt becoming the Divine Goodneſs not to deal ſo differently, that the Soul ſhould be everlaſtingly happy, and the Body loſt in forgetfulneſs; the one glorified in Heaven, the other remain in the Duſt. From their firſt ſetting out in the World to the Grave they ran the ſame Race, and ſhall enjoy the ſame Reward. Here the Body is the Conſort of the Soul in Obedience and Sufferings, hereafter in Fruition. When the Crown of Purity, or Palm of Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrdom ſhall be given by the great Judg in the view of all, they ſhall both partake in the honour. Of this we
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:62862:8"/>have an earneſt in the Reſurrection of Chriſt in his true Body, who <hi>is the firſt fruits of them that ſleep,</hi> 1 Cor. 15. <hi>He ſhall change our vile Bodies, that they may be faſhioned like to his glorious Body, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the working of his Power, whereby he is able to ſubdue all things to himſelf,</hi> Phil. 3.1. A ſubſtantial un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fading Glory will ſhine in them infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitely above the periſhing Pride of this World, that is but in appearance, like the ſalſe Colours painted on the Fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers of a Dove by the reflection of the Light, which preſently vaniſh, when it changeth its poſture, or the Light is withdrawn. Indeed what can be more glorious than to be conform'd to the Humanity of Chriſt, the Seat of all Beauty and Perfection. This Confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity ſhall be the Work of his own Hands. And when Omnipotence in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpoſes, nothing is difficult. The rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing the Body to an unchangeable ſtate of Glory, is as eaſie to the Divine Power, as the forming it at the firſt in the Womb. As the Sun labours no
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:62862:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>more in the Mines in the forming Gold and Silver, the moſt precious and du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Metals, than in the production of a poor ſhort-liv'd Flower.</p>
            <p>II. The Soul ſhall be made perfect in all its Faculties.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The Underſtanding ſhall clearly ſee the moſt excellent Objects. <hi>Now we know but in part,</hi> 1 Cor. 13. The naked beauty of Divine Things is vail'd, and of impoſſible diſcovery. And the weakneſs of the Mind is not proportionable to their dazling bright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs. But when that which is perfect is come, <hi>then that which is in part ſhall be done away.</hi> In that enlightned ſtate, the glorious manifeſtation of the Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects ſhall as much exceed the cleareſt revealing of them here, as the Sun in its full luſtre, one beam of light ſtrain'd through a crevice in the Wall. And the Underſtanding ſhall be prepar'd to take a full view of them. Therefore the Apoſtle compares the ſeveral Peri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ods of the Church, in reſpect of the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees of Knowledg, to the ſeveral Ages
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:62862:9"/>of this Life. <hi>When I was a Child, I ſpake as a Child, I underſtood as a Child, I thought as a Child: but when I became a Man, I put away childiſh things.</hi> In Children the Organs, either from an exceſs of moiſture, or their ſmalneſs, are indiſpoſed for the vigorous exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe of the Mind: ſome ſtrictures of Reaſon appear, a preſaging ſign what will be, but mixt with much obſcurity. But when the Organs are come to their juſt proportion and temperament, the Soul diſplays its ſtrength and activity.</p>
            <p>All things of a ſupernatural order ſhall then be clearly diſcovered. The con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trivance of our Salvation, the ways of conducting us to Bleſſedneſs, which are Objects of a ſublime nature, will afford an exquiſite pleaſure to the Under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding. All the ſecrets of our Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption ſhall be unſealed. <hi>The great Myſtery of Godlineſs,</hi> the Incarnation of the Eternal Son, and his according Juſtice with Mercy, ſhall then be ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parent. The Divine Counſels in go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verning the World, are now only vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:62862:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>in their wonderful effects, either of Mercy or Juſtice, and thoſe moſt dreadful; but the Reaſons of them are paſt finding out. But what our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our ſaid to <hi>Peter, What I do, thou know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt not now, but ſhalt know hereafter,</hi> is applicable to theſe impenetrable di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpenſations. All the original Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains of Wiſdom, as clear as deep, ſhall then be opened. We ſhall then ſee the beauty of Providence in diſpoſing temporal things in order to our eternal felicity. We now ſee as it were the rought part, and Knots of that curious Embroidery: but then the whole Work ſhall be unfolded, the ſweetneſs of the Colours and proportion of the Figures appear. There we ſhall be able to expound the perplexing Riddle, <hi>How out of the Eater came Meat, and out of the Strong came Sweetneſs. For we ſhall know as we are known.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>We ſhall ſee God.</hi> Our Saviour tells us, <hi>This is Life Eternal, to know thee the only true God, and Jeſus Chriſt whom thou haſt ſent.</hi> The beginning and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:62862:10"/>of our Happineſs conſiſts in this knowledg. The Deity is ſpiritual and inviſible to the Eye of the Body, infinite and incomprehenſible to the Soul. But we ſhall then ſo clearly un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand the <hi>Divine Perfections,</hi> that our preſent knowledg compar'd to that, is but as the ſeeing a dark reſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blance in a Glaſs, to the clear view of a Perſon in the native beauty of his Face. God is moſt gloriouſly preſent in Heaven. For according to the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees of excellence in the Work, ſuch are the impreſſions and diſcoveries of the Vertues of the Cauſe. Now all ſenſible things in the low order of Nature, are but weak reſultances from his Perfections, in compariſon of their illuſtrious Effects in the Divine World. The Glories of the Place, and of the Inhabitants, the Angels and Saints, clearly expreſs his Majeſty, Goodneſs and Power. But in a tranſcendent manner he exhibits himſelf in the glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied Mediator. He is ſtiled <hi>the Bright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of his Father's Glory, and the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:62862:11"/>Image of his Perſon;</hi> not only for his equal Perfections in reſpect of the unity of their Nature, but to ſignifie that God in the Perſon of the incar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate Mediator is ſo fully repreſented to us, that by the ſight of him we ſee God himſelf in his unchangeable Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellencies. This appears by the fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing words, that <hi>having purged us from our ſins, he ſate down on the right hand of the Majeſty on high;</hi> for they reſpect the Son of God as united to the humane Nature, in which he perform'd the Office of the Prieſthood, and took poſſeſſion of his glorious Kingdom. During his humble ſtate, the Divine Vertues, Wiſdom, Goodneſs, Holineſs, Power, were ſo viſible in his Perſon, Life, Revelations, and miraculous Works, that when <hi>Philip</hi> ſo long'd for the ſight of the Father as the only con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſummate Bleſſedneſs, <hi>Shew us the Father, and it ſuffices;</hi> He told him, <hi>He that has ſeen me, has ſeen the Father alſo.</hi> But how brightly do they appear in his triumphant Exaltation. 'Twas his
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:62862:11"/>Prayer on Earth; <hi>Father, I will that they alſo whom thou haſt given me, be with me where I am, that they may behold my Glory.</hi> Ineſtimable Felicity! Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther we conſider him in the reſpect of an Object, that incomparably tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcends all the created Glory of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, or in the relation of our Head, on a double account; partly becauſe he was debaſed into the form of a Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant, and ſuffered all Indignities and Cruelties of Sinners for us, has received the Recompence of his Meritorious Sufferings, the triumph of his Victory, <hi>being glorifled with the Father with the Glory he had before the World was;</hi> and partly becauſe every Member ſhall be conformed to him in his Glory; <hi>We ſhall be like him, for we ſhall ſee him as he is.</hi> And all Felicity and Glory is compriz'd in that Promiſe. The ſight of the Face of <hi>Moſes</hi> when radiant, had no transforming efficacy; for the light of it was not in him as its ſource, but by derivation. But God is Light <hi>eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentially,</hi> and the ſight of his Perfections
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:62862:12"/>will be productive of his <hi>Likeneſs</hi> in us, ſo far as it may be in a reſtrained Subject. When our Saviour was upon the <hi>holy Mount,</hi> and one vaniſhing Beam of Glory appear'd in his <hi>Transfiguration, Peter</hi> was ſo tranſported at the ſight, that he forgot the World and himſelf. How raviſhing then will the ſight of him be in his triumphant Majeſty, when we ſhall be transfigured our ſelves?</p>
            <p n="2">2. As we ſhall behold God's Face, know his moſt amiable Excellencies; ſo they ſhall love him as perfectly as they know him. To the illuſtrations of the Mind, there are correſpondent impreſſions on the Heart. In the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent ſtate our Love is imperfect, and as Fire out of its ſphere, dies away, by our neglect to feed it with proper ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terials, enamouring conſiderations of God. But 'tis not ſo in Heaven: there the Divine Sun attracts every Eye with the light of its Beauty, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flames every Heart with the heat of his Love. The continual Preſence of God
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:62862:12" rendition="simple:additions"/>is in different reſpects the Cauſe and Effect of our Love to him. For there is no more powerful Attractive to love him, than to ſee him; And Love keeps the Thoughts undivided from him. <hi>God is Love,</hi> and will kindle in us a pure Affection that Eternity ſhall ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver leſſen.</p>
            <p>Our Affections that are now ſcat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered on many things, wherein ſome ſmall Reflections of his Goodneſs ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear, ſhall joyn in one full Current in Heaven, where <hi>God is all in all.</hi> We ſhall then underſtand the riches of his Love, that God who is infinitely hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py in himſelf, ſhould make Man for ſuch a Glory, and ſuch a Glory for Man. And that when for his Rebelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on he was juſtly expell'd from Paradiſe, and under a ſentence of Eternal Death, God ſhould pleaſe to reſtore him to his Favour, and to give him a better ſtate than was forfeited. We ſhall then un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand our infinite Obligations to the Son of God, who deſcended from the Heaven of Heavens to our Earth;
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:62862:13"/>and which is more, from the Majeſty wherein he there reign'd, from the Glory wherein he was viſible to the Angelical Minds, and became Man for Men, Redemption for the Loſt, to purchaſe Immortal Life for thoſe who were dead to that bleſſed Life. In ſhort, then God will expreſs his Love to us in the higheſt degrees that a finite Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture is capable to receive from Love it ſelf, and we ſhall love him with all the ſtrength of our glorified Powers.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Compleat ſatisfaction flows from union with God by Knowledg and Love. <hi>In his Preſence is fulneſs of Joy, at his Right-hand are Pleaſures for ever.</hi> The Cauſes and Excellencies of the Heavenly Life are in thoſe words ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſt. The Cauſes are the influxive Preſence of God, the revelation of his attractive Perfections, the beholding his Face, the declaration of his peculi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ar Favour. This our bleſſed Lord him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf had a reſpect to, as the compleat Reward of his Sufferings: <hi>Thou ſhalt make me full of Joy with thy Countenance.</hi>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:62862:13" rendition="simple:additions"/>And his <hi>Right-hand,</hi> his Bounty, that diſpenſes, and Power that ſecures that Felicity. The Excellencies of this State are fulneſs of Joy, and that without di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minution, or end.</p>
            <p>When the Soul opens its eyes to the clear diſcoveries of the firſt Truth, and its breaſt to the dear and intimate im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braces of the Supream Good, beyond which nothing remains to be known, nothing to be enjoy'd, what a deluge of the pureſt Pleaſures will overflow it? We cannot aſcend in our thoughts ſo high, as to conceive the exceſs of Joy that attends thoſe operations of the glorified Soul upon its proper Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject. But ſomething we may conje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture.</p>
            <p n="1">(1.) Thoſe who are poſſeſt with a noble Paſſion for Knowledg, how do they deſpiſe all lower Pleaſures in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pariſon of it? How do they forget themſelves, neglect the Body, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tire into the Mind, the higheſt part of Man, and neareſt to God? The bare
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:62862:14"/>apprehenſion of ſuch things that by their internal nature have no attractive influence upon the Affections, is plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant to the Underſtanding. As the appearance of Light, though not at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended with any other viſible Beauties, refreſhes the Eye after long darkneſs: ſo the clear diſcovery of Truths, how abſtract ſo-ever, that were before un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>known, is grateful to the intellective Faculty. Thus ſome have been ſtrange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly tranſported with the pleaſures of a Mathematical Demonſtration, when the Evidence, not the Importance of the Thing was ſo raviſhing: for what is more dry and barren of delight than the ſpeculation of Figures and Num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers? <hi>Solon</hi> when near his end, and ſome of his Friends that viſited him were ſpeaking ſoftly of a Point of Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophy, by a ſound of Wiſdom was awaken'd from the ſleep of Death that was juſt ſeizing on him, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pening his Eyes, and raiſing his Head to give attention; being ask'd the
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:62862:14"/>reaſon of it? Anſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, <hi>That when</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>t cum iſtud quicquid eſt de quo diſp it at is percepcro, moriar. <hi>Val. Max.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>I un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand what you are diſcourſing of, I may die.</hi> Such was his delight in Knowledg, that a little of it made his Agony inſenſible. But here are many Imperfections that leſſen this intellectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Pleaſure, which ſhall ceaſe in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven. Here the acquiſition of Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg is often with the expence of Health: the flower of the Spirits, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary for Natural Operations, is wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted by intenſe thoughts. How often are the Learned ſickly? As the Flint when 'tis ſtruck, gives not a ſpark without conſuming it ſelf; So Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg is obtain'd by Studies that waſte our faint ſenſitive Faculties. But then our Knowledg ſhall be a free emanation from the Spring of Truth, without our labour and pains. Here we learn by circuit, and diſcern by comparing things; our Ignorance is diſpell'd by a gradual ſucceſſion of Light: But then Univerſal Knowledg ſhall be infuſed in
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:62862:15" rendition="simple:additions"/>a moment. Here after all our labour and toyl, how little Knowledg do we gain? Every Queſtion is a Labyrinth, out of which the nimbleſt and moſt ſearching Minds cannot extricate them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves. How many ſpecious Errors impoſe upon our Underſtandings? We look on things by falſe Lights, through deceiving Spectacles: But then our Knowledg ſhall be certain and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleat. There is no forbidden Tree in the Celeſtial Paradiſe, as no inordinate Affection. But ſuppoſe that all things in the compaſs of the World were known, yet ſtill there would be empti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and anguiſh in the Mind: for the moſt comprehenſive knowledg of things that are inſufficient to make us happy, cannot afford true Satisfaction. But then we ſhall ſee God in all his Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellencies, the ſupream Object and End, the only Felicity of the Soul. How will the ſight of his Glory perſonally ſhining in our Redeemer, in the firſt moment quench our extream thirſt, and fill us with joy and admiration? 'Tis
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:62862:15"/>not as the naked conception of Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures, that only makes rich in <hi>ideas,</hi> but that Divine ſight gives a real Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt in him. The Angels are ſo raviſh'd with the Beauties and Wonders of his Face, that they never divert a moment from the contemplation of it.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The pure Love of the Saints to God is then fully ſatisfied. Love con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered as an affection of Friendſhip, is always attended with two deſires; to be aſſured of Reciprocal Love, and to enjoy the Converſation of the Perſon beloved, the teſtimony of his eſteem and good-will. This kind of<note n="*" place="margin">Ariſtot.</note> Affection ſeems to be inconſiſtent with that infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite diſtance that is between God and the Creature. But though 'tis diſpro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portionable to the Divine Majeſty, 'tis proportionable to his Goodneſs. Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly our Saviour Promiſes, <hi>He that loves me, ſhall be loved of my Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and I will love him, and will ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt my ſelf unto him.</hi> And to confirm our belief of this aſtoniſhing Conde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcention,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:62862:16"/>repeats it, <hi>If a Man love me, my Father will love him, and we will come to him, and make our abode with him.</hi> In the preſent ſtate, the ſigns of God's ſpecial favour are exhibited to his Friends. Now he beſtows on them the Honour of being his Sons, the Graces and Comforts of his Spirit, the precious Earneſts of his Love, and <hi>Seal of their Redemption.</hi> But in eminency of degrees, the effects of his Love are incomparably more glorious in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven. Here the Saints are Adopted, there Crown'd. There he opens all the bright Treaſures of his Wiſdom, the Riches of his Goodneſs, the Beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of his Holineſs, the Glories of his Power, and by the intimate applicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of his Preſence, makes his Love moſt ſenſible to them. O the mutual delights between God and glorified Souls! God looks on them with an en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaged Eye, as his own by many dear Titles, and is well-pleaſed in his own Goodneſs to them, and raviſh'd with the reflex of his own Excellencies ſhin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:62862:16"/>in them. <hi>As the Bridegroom rejoyces over the Bride,</hi> ('tis the Language of Divine Love) <hi>ſo their God rejoyces over them.</hi> And what a bleſſed Reſt do they find in the compleat fruition of their Beloved? All their deſires quietly ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire in his Boſom. What Triumphs of Joy follow? Can we frame a fuller Conception of Happineſs, than to be perfectly loved by infinite Goodneſs, and perfectly to love him?</p>
            <p n="3">3. The ſupreme Joy of the Saints is for the Felicity and Glory of God himſelf. For as the Holy Soul feels no more powerful motive to love God, than becauſe he is moſt worthy of it, as he is God, a Being of infinite Excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lencies, and therefore to be loved above the deareſt Perſons and Things, even it ſelf; ſo the higheſt Joy it partakes of is from this conſideration, That God is infinitely bleſſed and glorious. For in this the ſupream deſire of Love is ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſh'd, that the moſt beloved Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject is perfectly honour'd and pleaſed. In Heaven the Love of the Saints to
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:62862:17" rendition="simple:additions"/>God is in its higheſt Perfection; and they ſee his Glory in the moſt perfect manner, which cauſes a tranſcendent Joy to them. And this is one reaſon why the Saints, though ſhining with unequal degrees of Glory, are equally content. For their moſt ardent Love being ſet on <hi>God,</hi> that he is pleas'd to glorifie himſelf by ſuch various com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munications of his Goodneſs, is full ſatisfaction to their deſires. Beſides, in thoſe different degrees of Glory, every one is ſo content with his own,<note n="*" place="margin">Sic itaque ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bebit donum aliud alio minus, ut hic quoque donum ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beat ne velit am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plius. <hi>Aug.</hi>
               </note> that there is no poſſible deſire of being but what he is.</p>
            <p n="4">4. The full joy of Heaven ſhall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue without diminution, or end.</p>
            <p>Firſt, The number of Poſſeſſors can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not leſſen it. The Divine Preſence is an unwaſted Spring of Pleaſure equal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly full and open to all, and abundantly ſufficient to ſatisfy the immenſity of their deſires. Envy reigns in this World, becauſe earthly things are ſo imperfect
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:62862:17" rendition="simple:additions"/>in their Nature, and ſo peculiar in their Poſſeſſion, that they cannot ſuffice, nor be enjoyed by all. But in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven none is touch'd with that low baſe paſſion: for God contains all that is pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious &amp; deſirable in the higheſt Degrees of Perfection, and all partake of the influence of his Univerſal Goodneſs without intercepting one another. In the Kingdom above there is no cauſe for the Elder Brother to repine at the Father's Bounty to the Younger, nor for the Younger to ſupplant the Elder, to obtain the Birth-right. The Heirs of God are all rais'd to Sovereign Glory. Every one enjoys him as en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tirely and fully, as if ſolely his felicity. God is a <hi>Good</hi> as <hi>indiviſible</hi> as <hi>infinite,</hi> and not diminiſh'd by the moſt liberal communications of Himſelf. We may illuſtrate this by comparing the Price of our Redemption, and the Reward. The Death of Chriſt is an univerſal be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit to all the Saints, yet 'tis ſo appli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to every Believer for his perfect Redemption, as if our Saviour in all
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:62862:18" rendition="simple:additions"/>his Agonies and Sufferings had no other in his Eye and Heart; as if all his Prayers, his Tears, his Blood were offer'd up to his Father only for that Perſon. The common reſpect of it the Apoſtle declares in thoſe admirable words, that ſignifie ſuch an exceſs of God's Love to us, <hi>He that ſpared not his own Son, but deliver'd him up for us all, how ſhall he not with him alſo freely give us all things?</hi> But to imagine that<note n="*" place="margin">Et totum ſe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit univerſis, &amp; to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum ſingulis. Ac per hoc quicquid paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>one ſua Salvator praeſtitit, ſicut to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum ei debent uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſi, ſic ſinguli; niſi quod prope hoc plus ſinguli quam univerſi, quod to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum acceperunt ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guli quantum uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſi, <hi>Salvian.</hi>
               </note> the propriety of every Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liever is thereby pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judiced, is not only falſe, but extreamly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jurious to the Merit and Dignity, and to the infinite Love of Chriſt. Therefore the ſame Apoſtle tells us, <hi>The Life which I now live in the fleſh, I live by the Faith of the Son of God; who loved me, and gave himſelf for me:</hi> as if he were the ſole Object of Chriſt's Love, the End
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:62862:18"/>and Reward of his Sufferings. And this appropriating of it to himſelf, is no prejudice to the rights of all others. St. <hi>John</hi> deſcribes himſelf by that truly glorious Title, <hi>The Diſciple whom Jeſus loved.</hi> Could he ſpeak this of himſelf without the injury and indignation of the other Diſciples? Certainly he might. For if we conſider that incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſible Love of Chriſt, expreſt to them all at his laſt Supper, after <hi>Judas</hi> was gone forth; <hi>As the Father hath lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved me, ſo have I loved you.</hi> We may eaſily underſtand, that every one of them might juſtly believe that he was ſingularly beloved of Chriſt. They were all received in the Heart, though (with <hi>John</hi>) they did not all lean on the Breaſt of their Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Maſter. Thus in Heaven God is the U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niverſal Treaſure of all the Saints, and the pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culiar Portion of every one.<note n="*" place="margin">Si audiat multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudo ſilens, non in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſe particulatim comminnunt ſonos, tanquam cibos: ſed omne quod ſonat &amp; omnibus totum eſt, &amp; ſingulis totum. <hi>Auguſt. in Epiſt. ad Voluſan.</hi>
               </note> As by his Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence he equally fills
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:62862:19"/>the whole World, and every part of it; and by his Providence equally re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gards all and every particular Creature; ſo in Heaven he diſpenſes the Riches of his Love to all, that they cannot deſire more, if every one of them were (if I may ſo expreſs it) the only begotten of <hi>the only begotten himſelf,</hi> the ſole Heir of all the Merits of his Son. Every Saint may with the inflamed Spouſe break forth in that Triumph of Love; <hi>My Beloved is mine, and I am his.</hi> Nay, the great number of the glorifi'd Saints is ſo far from leſſening their Joy, that it unſpeakably encreaſes it. <hi>The innume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Company of Angels, and the General Aſſembly of the Church of the Firſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>born,</hi> next to the happineſs of enjoying God, are a chief part of Heaven. An unfeigned ardent Affection unites that pure Society. Our Love is now kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led either from a relation in Nature, or ſome viſible Excellencies that render a Perſon worthy of our choice and friendſhip: but in Heaven the Reaſons are greater, and the degrees of Love
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:62862:19"/>incomparably more fervent. All Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Alliances and Reſpects ceaſe in that Supernatural State. The Apoſtle tells us, <hi>If I have known Chriſt after the fleſh, I know him ſo no more.</hi> By the Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection and Aſcenſion of Chriſt he was tranſported into another World, and had communion with him as an Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly King, without low regards to the temporal priviledge of converſing with him on Earth. The Spiritual relation is more near and permanent than the ſtricteſt band of Nature. The Saints have all relation to the ſame Heavenly Father, and to <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> the Prince of Peace, and Head of that happy Fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternity. The principal motive of Love here, is for the inherent Excellencies of a Perſon. Wiſdom, Goodneſs, Holineſs, are mighty Attractives, and produce a more worthy Affection, a more intimate Confederacy of Souls, than propinqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty in Nature. <hi>David</hi> declares that <hi>all his delight was in the Excellent.</hi> But there are allays of this Noble Love here. For,</p>
            <p n="1">1. There are reliques of Frailty in
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:62862:20"/>the beſt Men on Earth, ſome Blemiſhes that render them leſs amiable when diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered. Here their Graces are mixt Infirmities, and but aſcending to Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry. Accordingly our Love to them muſt be regular, and ſerene; not clouded with Error, miſtaking defects for ami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able qualities. But in Heaven the Image of God is compleat, by the union of all the glorious Vertues requiſit to its per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection. Every Saint there exactly a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees with the firſt <hi>Exemplar,</hi> is tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed according to the primitive beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of Holineſs. No <hi>ſpot or wrinkle re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mains,</hi> or any ſuch thing, that may caſt the leaſt aſpect of deformity upon them.</p>
            <p n="2">2. In the preſent ſtate, the leaſt part of the Saints worth is viſible. As the Earth is fruitful in Plants and Flowers, but its Riches are in the Mines of pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Metals, the veins of Marble hid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den in its boſom. True, Grace appears in ſenſible Actions, <hi>but its Glory is with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in.</hi> The ſincerity of Aims, the purity of Affections, the impreſſes of the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit on the Heart, the interiour Beauties
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:62862:20" rendition="simple:additions"/>of Holineſs, are only ſeen by God. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, ſuch is the humility of eminent Saints, that the more they abound in Spiritual Treaſures, the leſs they ſhew. As the Heavenly Bodies when in neareſt conjunction with the Sun, and fulleſt of light, make the leaſt appearance to our ſight. But all their Excellencies ſhall then be in view. <hi>The Glory of God ſhall be revealed in them.</hi> And how attractive is the Divine Likeneſs to an holy Eye? How will it raviſh the Saints to behold an immortal Lovelineſs ſhining in one another? Their Love is mutual and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flexive, proportionable to the Cauſe of it. An equal conſtant Flame is preſery'd by pure materials. Every one is perfectly amiable, and perfectly enamour'd with all. Now can we frame a fuller Concep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Happineſs, than ſuch a State of Love, wherein whateyer is pleaſant in Friendſhip is in perfection, and whatever is diſtaſtful by Mens folly and weakneſs is aboliſh'd. The Pſalmiſt breaks out in a Rapture, <hi>Behold how good and pleaſant it is for Brethren to dwell together in <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty!</hi>
               <pb n="36" facs="tcp:62862:21"/>Love is the Beauty and Strength of Societies, the Pleaſure of Life. How excellent is the Joy of the Bleſſed, when the Prayer of Chriſt ſhall be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſh'd, that they all may be <hi>one! As thou, Father, art in me, and I in thee, that they alſo may be one in us.</hi> God is abſolutely One in his glorious Nature and Will, and therefore unalterably happy; And their inviolable Union in Love, is a Ray of the Eſſential Unity between the ſacred Perſons. There are no Diviſions of Heart and Tongues, as in this <hi>Babel,</hi> but the moſt perfect and ſweeteſt Concord, an Eternal Agreement in Tempers and Inclinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. There are no envious Compari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons; for Love that affectively tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forms one into another, cauſes the Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of every Saint to redound to the Joy of all. Every one takes his ſhare in the Felicity of all, and adds to it. Such is the power of that Celeſtial Fire wherein they all burn, that it melts and mixes Souls in ſuch an entire Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that by Complacence and an inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:62862:21"/>Joy, the Bleſſedneſs of all is, as it were, proper to every one; as if eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one were plac'd in the Hearts of all, and all in the Heart of every one. If in the Church of the firſt-born Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, in the earthly <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> the Band of Charity was ſo ſtrict, that 'tis ſaid, the <hi>Multitude of Believers were of one Heart, and one Soul;</hi> How much more intimate and inſeparable is the Union of the Saints in <hi>Jeruſalem above,</hi> where eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one loves another as himſelf?</p>
            <p>'Tis recorded of <hi>Alexander,</hi> that en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tring with <hi>Haepheſtion</hi> his Favourite, into the Pavilion of <hi>Darius</hi>'s Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, then his Priſoner, ſhe bowed to the Favourite, as having a greater ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance of Majeſty, thinking him to be <hi>Alexander;</hi> but adviſed of her Error, ſhe humbly begg'd his Pardon, to whom the generous King repli'd,<note place="margin">Non errâſti, Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, nam hic <hi>Ale<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xander</hi> eſt. <hi>Curt. l. 3.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>You did not err, Mother, for this is alſo Alexander.</hi> Such was their Affection, that whoever was taken of them, the other was taken in him; the leſs aſcending in the
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:62862:22"/>greater, without degrading the greater in the leſs. This is a Copy of the holy Love of the Bleſſed; but with the ſame difference, as between the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription of a Star with a Coal, and its Beauty in its proper Aſpect. And where all is Love, all is Delight. O how do they enjoy and triumph in the Happineſs of one another? With what an unimaginable tenderneſs do they embrace? What Reciprocations of Endearments are between them? O their raviſhing Converſation, and ſweet Entercourſe! for their Preſence together in Heaven is not a ſilent Show. In the Transfiguration, <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Elias</hi> talkt with Chriſt. With what excellent Diſcourſes do they entertain one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther? If <hi>David</hi> felt ſuch inward plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure from the ſence of God's favours, that he could not reſtrain the expreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of it, but invites the Saints, <hi>Come and hear, all ye that fear the Lord, and I will tell you what he has done for my Soul.</hi> Certainly in Heaven, the Bleſſed with over-flowing Affections recount
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:62862:22"/>the Divine Benefits, the admirable Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thods, whereby the Life of Grace was begun, preſerv'd and carried on in the midſt of Temptations; the continual Succeſſion of Mercies in the time of their Hopes, and the Conſummation of all in the time of their Enjoyment. How joyfully do they concur in their Thankſgivings to God for the good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of Creation, in making them rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable Creatures, capable to know, love and enjoy Him, when they might have been of the loweſt Order in the whole Sphere of Beings; for his compaſſionate Care and Providence over them in this World. But eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally for his Sovereign Mercy in electing them to be Veſſels of honour; for his powerful Grace, in reſcuing them from the cruel and ignominious bondage of Sin; for his moſt free Love, that juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied them from all their Guilt by the Death of his only Son, and glorified them with himſelf. They are never weary in this delightful Exerciſe, but continually bleſs him for his Mercy
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:62862:23" rendition="simple:additions"/>that endures for ever. We may judge by the Saints here, when they are in a fit diſpoſition to praiſe God, what Fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours they feel in their united Praiſes of him in Heaven. The Pſalmiſt in an Extaſy calls to all the parts of the World to joyn with him; <hi>The Lord reigns, let the Heavens rejoyce, and the Earth be glad; let the Sea roar, let the Fields be joyful, and all that dwell there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in.</hi> He deſires that Nature ſhould be elevated above it ſelf, that the dead parts be inſpir'd with life, the inſenſible feel motions of joy, and thoſe that want a voice, break forth in praiſes, to adorn the Divine Triumph. With what Life and Alacrity will the Saints in their bleſſed Communion celebrate the Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject of their Love and Praiſes? The <hi>Seraphims</hi> about the Throne <hi>cry'd to one another,</hi> to expreſs their Zeal and Joy, in celebrating his Eternal Purity and Power, and the Glory of his Goodneſs. Oh the unſpeakable Pleaſure of this Concert! when every Soul is harmo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nious, and contributes his Part to the
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:62862:23" rendition="simple:additions"/>Muſick of Heaven! O could we hear but ſome <hi>Eccho</hi> of thoſe Songs wherewith the Heaven of Heavens re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſounds, ſome remains of thoſe Voices wherewith the Saints above <hi>triumph in the Praiſes,</hi> in the ſolemn Adoration of the King of Spirits, how would it in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flame our deſires to be joyn'd with them? <hi>Bleſſed are thoſe that are in thy Houſe, they always praiſe Thee.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. The fulneſs of Joy in Heaven is undecaying; for the cauſes of it are al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways equal. And thoſe are the Beati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fick Object reveal'd, and the uninter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted Contemplation of it.</p>
            <p>Whilſt we are here below, the Sun of Righteouſneſs, as to our perception and ſence, has aſcenſions and declina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, acceſſes and receſſes. And our Earth is not ſo purified, but ſome Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pours ariſe that intercept his chearfull refreſhing Light. From hence there are alternate ſucceſſions of Spiritual Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts and Sorrows, of Doubts and filial Confidence in the Saints. 'Tis a rare favour of Heaven, when an humble Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liever
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:62862:24"/>in his whole courſe is ſo circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect as not to provoke God to appear diſpleaſed againſt him: When a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian (as thoſe tutelar Angels ſpoken of in the Goſpel) always beholds the face of his Heavenly Father, and converſes with him with an holy Liberty. And what a torment the <hi>hiding of God's face</hi> is to a deſerted Soul, only they know who feel it. External troubles are ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny times attended with more Conſola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions to the Spirit, than Afflictions to Senſe; but to love God with a tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeendent Affection, and to fear he is our Enemy, no puniſhment exceeds, or is equal to it. As his Loving-kindneſs in their eſteem is better than Life, ſo his Diſpleaſure is worſe than Death. How do they wreſtle with God by Prayers and Tears, and offer as it were, a holy Violence to the King of Heaven, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover their firſt ſerenity of Mind, the loſt Peace of Heart? How paſſionately do they cry out, with <hi>Job,</hi> in the Book of his Patience, (Job 29.2, 3, 4.) <hi>O that I were as in months paſt, as in the
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:62862:24" rendition="simple:additions"/>day taken God preſerved me: when his Candle ſhin'd upon my Head, and when by his Light I walk'd through darkneſs: As I was in the days of my youth, when the Seoret of God was upon my Tabernacle.</hi> And ſometimes God delayes the reveal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing himſelf even to his deareſt Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren; not that he does not ſee their Neceſſities, and hear their Prayers, or is ſo hard that till their Extremities he is not moved with Compaſſion, but for wiſe and holy Reaſons; Either <hi>that they may not return to Folly,</hi> if by any pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumptuous Sin they forfeited their Peaces; or if they have been careful to pleaſe him, yet he may deprive them of Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual Comforts for a time, to keep them humble, and that with an obedient re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſignation to his Sovereign Pleaſure they may wait for his reviving Preſence. And then Joy returns greater than be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore. For thus God uſually renders with intereſt what he ſuſpended only for trial. But the Saints above are for ever enlightned with the vital ſplendor and dear regards of his Countenance,
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:62862:25" rendition="simple:additions"/>always enjoy his beamy ſmiles. A con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinual effuſion of Glory illuſtrates Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven and all its bleſſed Inhabitants.</p>
            <p>And their Contemplation of God is ſixed. If the Object, though extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary glorious, were tranſient, or the Eye ſo weak that it could only ſee it but by glances, the heighth of Joy would not be perpetual. But the Mind is prepar'd with ſupernatural vigour, to ſee the brightneſs of God's Face, and by the moſt attentive application al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways converſes with that bleſſed Object, ſo that the Joy of Heaven is never in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termitted for a moment. They always ſee, and love, and rejoyce, and praiſe him.</p>
            <p>'Tis poſſible a carnal Suſpition may ariſe in ſome, as if the uniform perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual Viſion of the ſame Glory might loſe its perfect delightfulneſs. For thoſe who ſeek for happineſs in the va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity of the Creatures, are always deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous of Change, and have their Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments ſo corrupted, that while they languiſh with a ſecret deſire after an
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:62862:25"/>unchangeable Good, yet they conceive no Good as deſirable, that is not changed.</p>
            <p>But to correct this groſs Errour of Fancy, let us a little enquire into the Cauſes of Diſſatisfaction, that make the conſtant fruition of the ſame thing here to be tedious.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Senſible things are of ſuch a limi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Goodneſs, that not any of them can ſupply all our preſent wants, ſo that 'tis neceſſary to leave one for ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. And the moſt of them are Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medies of our diſeaſed Appetites, and if not temperately uſed, are deſtructive Evils. Eating and Drinking are to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinguiſh Hunger and Thirſt, but con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued beyond juſt meaſure become nauſeous. Beſides, the Inſufficiency of their Objects, the Senſes themſelves cannot be ſatisfied all at once. The Ear cannot attend to delightful Sounds, and the Eye be intent on beautiful Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lours at the ſame time: the Satisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of one Senſe defeats another of en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joying its proper good; therefore the
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:62862:26"/>ſame Object is not conſtantly pleaſant, but the Heart is diſtemper'd from as many Cauſes, as there are deſires unac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſh'd. Add further, all things under the Sun afford only a ſuperficial delight, and miſerably deceive the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectations raiſed of them: and many times there is a mixture of ſome evil in them, that is more offenſive than the good is delightful. The Honey is at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended with a Sting, ſo that often thoſe things we ſigh after through vehement deſire, when they are obtain'd, we ſigh for grief. Now all theſe Cauſes of diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſatisfaction ceaſe in in Heaven; for<note n="*" place="margin">Vitae nos taedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um tene<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, timor mortis natat omne conſilium, nec im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plere nos ulla foeli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s poteſt. Cauſa autem eſt, quod non pervenimus ad il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ud bonum immen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſum &amp; inſuperabile, ubi neceſſe eſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtat nobis volun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tas noſtra, quia ul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tra ſummum non eſt locus. <hi>Son. ep. 74.</hi>
               </note> God is an infinite Good, and whatever is truly deſirable and precious is in him in all degrees of Perfection. And in his Preſence all the powers of the Soul are drawn out in their moſt pleaſant exerciſe, and always enjoy their
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:62862:26"/>entire happineſs. The Fruition of him exceeds our moſt raiſed hopes, as much as he is more glorious in Himſelf than in any borrowed Repreſentations. God will be to us incomparably <hi>above what we can ask or think.</hi> The Compaſs of of our thoughts, the Depth of our de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires are imperfect Meaſures of his Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections. And as he is a <hi>Pure Good</hi> in Himſelf, ſo he is prevalent over all Evil. 'Tis evident therefore, that no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing can allay the Joys of Saints when they are in God's preſence.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Novelty is not requiſite to ingra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiate every Good, and make it perfectly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightful.<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> Ariſt. Eth. lib. 7. c. ult.</note> God is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finitely happy, to whom no Good was ever new. 'Tis indeed the Sauce that gives a delicious taſte to inferiour things. For Men reliſh only what is eminent, and the good things of this World are ſo truly mean, that they are fain to borrow a ſhew of Greatneſs by compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſon
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:62862:27"/>with a worſe eſtate preceding. But an infinite Good produces always the ſame pure equal compleat Joy, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it ariſes from its intrinſick per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection, that wants no Foil to commend it. The Pſalmiſt breaks forth, <hi>Whom have I in Heaven but Thee?</hi> This is no vaniſhing Rapture, but a conſtant joy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful height of Affection. God the eſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial Happineſs of the Saints, is always perfectly lovely and delightful to them.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The glorified Saints in every pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riod of their happy ſtate, have as lively a perception of it as in the beginning. To make this evident, we muſt conſider that the pleaſure of Novelty ſprings from a quick ſenſe of the oppoſit terms, between our condition in the want of ſome deſired Good, and after our ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining it. Now the Mind is more in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenſe on the advantage, and more ſtrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly affected at firſt. One newly freed from the torments of a ſharp Diſeaſe, feels a greater pleaſure than from a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant tenour of Health. Thoſe who are
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:62862:27" rendition="simple:additions"/>rais'd from a low State to eminent Dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, are tranſported with their firſt change; but in tract of time the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance of their mean condition is ſo weakned and ſpent, that 'tis like the ſhadow of a Dream, and proportion<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ably their Joy is leſſened. Honours, like Perfumes, by cuſtom are leſs ſenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to thoſe that carry them. But the Saints above always conſider and feel the excellent difference between their ſuffering and triumphant ſtate. They never loſe that raviſhing part of Feli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city, the vivid ſence of paſt evils. Their reflections are always as ſtrong on the Miſery from whence they were rais'd to the pitch of Happineſs, as in their firſt glorious Tranſlation. In what an Extaſy of wonder and pleaſure will they be, from the freſh memory of what they were, and the joyful ſence of what they are? <hi>I was</hi> (ſays the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miring Soul) <hi>poor, blind, and naked;</hi> but O miraculous and happy Altera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion! I am full of Light, enrich'd with the Treaſures of Heaven, adorn'd with di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:62862:28" rendition="simple:additions"/>Glory. I was under the tyrannous power of Satan, <hi>but he is bruiſed under my feet.</hi> I was ſentenc'd to an ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting Separation from the Preſence of God, my only Life and Joy; but now am poſſeſt of my ſupream Good. O how tranſporting is the compariſon of theſe wide and contrary Extreams? How beautiful and pleaſant is the Day of Eternity, after ſuch a dark tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peſtuous Night? How does the remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of ſuch Evils produce a more lively and feeling fruition of ſuch Hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs? How ſtrangely and mightily does <hi>Salvation with Eternal Glory affect the Soul?</hi> This gives a ſpritely accent to their everlaſting <hi>Hallelujahs.</hi> This preſerves an affectionate heat in their Thankſgivings to their Victorious De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liverer. And thus their Happineſs is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways the ſame, and always new. Their Pleaſure is continued in its perfection.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Laſtly.</hi> The Bleſſedneſs of the Saints is without end. This makes Heaven to be it ſelf. There is no ſatiety of the preſent, no ſollicitude for the future.
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:62862:28"/>Were there a poſſibility, or the leaſt ſuſpicion of loſing that happy ſtate, it would caſt an aſperſion of bitterneſs upon all their delights: they could not enjoy one moments repoſe; but the more excellent their Happineſs is, the more ſtinging would their fear be of parting with it. <hi>But the Inheritance re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved in Heaven, is immortal, undefiled, and fades not away.</hi> And the tenure of their Poſſeſſion is infinitely firm by the Divine Power, the true Support of their everlaſting Duration. <hi>With God is the Fountain of Life.</hi> They enjoy a better Immortality, than the Tree of Life could have preſerv'd in <hi>Adam.</hi> The Revolutions of the Heavens, and Ages, are under their Feet, and cannot in the leaſt alter or determine their Hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs. After the paſſing of millions of Years, ſtill an entire Eternity remains of their enjoying God. O moſt deſirable ſtate where Bleſſedneſs and Eternity are inſeparably united. O joyful Harmony! when the full <hi>Chorus</hi> of Heaven ſhall ſing, <hi>This God is our God for ever and
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:62862:29"/>ever.</hi> This adds an infinite weight to their Glory. This redoubles their unſpeakable Joys with infinite ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and ſecurity. They repoſe them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in the compleat fruition of their Happineſs. God reigns in the Saints, and they live in him for ever.</p>
            <p>From what has been diſcourſed we ſhould,</p>
            <p n="1">1. Conſider the woful Folly of Men in refuſing ſuch an Happineſs, that by the admirable Favour of God is offer'd to their choice. Can there be an Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectation, or Deſire, or Capacity in Man of enjoying an Happineſs beyond what is Infinite and Eternal? O blind and wretched World! ſo careleſs of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verlaſting Felicity. Who can behold, without compaſſion and indignation, Men vainly ſeeking for Happineſs where 'tis not to be found, and after innume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable diſappointments fly to an Impoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibility, and neglect their ſovereign and finàl Bleſſedneſs? Aſtoniſhing Madneſs! that God and Heaven ſhould be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſed
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:62862:29" rendition="simple:additions"/>in compariſon of painted Trifles. This adds the greateſt Contumely to their Impiety. What powerful Charm obſtructs their true judging of things? What Spirit of Errour poſſeſſes them? Alas, <hi>Eternal things are unſeen!</hi> not of conſpicuous moment, and therefore in the carnal Ballance are eſteemed light, againſt temporal things preſent to the Senſe. <hi>It does not appear what we ſhall be:</hi> The Vail of the viſible Heavens co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers the Sanctuary, where JESUS our High-Prieſt is entred, and ſtops the enquiring Eye.</p>
            <p>But have we not aſſurance by the moſt infallible Principles of Faith, that the Son of God came down from Heaven to live with us, and dy for us, and that he roſe again to confirm our Belief in his <hi>excee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding great and precious Promiſes</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning this happineſs in the Future State? And do not the moſt evident Principles of Reaſon and univerſal Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience prove, that this World can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not afford true Happineſs to us? How wretchedly do we forfeit the Preroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:62862:30"/>of the reaſonable Nature, by neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lecting our laſt and bleſſed End? If the Mind be darkned, that it does not ſee the amiable Excellencies of God, and the Will ſo depraved that it does not feel their raviſhing power; the Man ceaſes to be a Man, and becomes like the Beaſts that periſh. As a blind Eye is no longer an Eye, being abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely uſeleſs to that end for which it was made. And though in this preſent ſtate Men are ſtupid and unconcern'd, yet hereafter their Miſery will awaken them, to diſcover what is that Supream Good wherein their Perfection and Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licity conſiſts. When their folly ſhall be expoſed before God, Angels, and Saints, in what extream confuſion will they appear before that glorious and immenſe Theatre? Our Saviour told the unbelieving <hi>Jews, There ſhall be weeping, and gnaſhing of teeth, when ye ſhall ſee</hi> Abraham, <hi>and</hi> Iſaac, <hi>and</hi> Ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob, <hi>and all the Prophets in the Kingdom of God, and you your ſelves turn'd out.</hi> They ſhall be tortur'd with the deſire
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:62862:30" rendition="simple:additions"/>of Happineſs without poſſible ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction. 'Tis moſt juſt that thoſe who err without excuſe, ſhould repent with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out remedy.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Let us be excited ſeriouſly to apply our ſelves in the uſe of effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctual means for the obtaining this Hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs. Indeed the original Cauſe of it, is the pure rich Mercy of God; the meritorious, is the moſt precious Obedience of our Saviour, by whom we obtain <hi>plenteous Redemption.</hi> His Abaſement is the cauſe of our Exaltati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. The Wounds he received in his Body the Characters of Ignominy, and Footſteps of Death, are the Fountains of our Glory. <hi>Eternal Life is the Gift of God through Jeſus Christ our Lord.</hi> But the Goſpel declares; <hi>That without Holineſs no Man ſhall ſee God.</hi> An ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly change of our Natures, and perſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance in the Courſe of univerſal Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, are indiſpenſibly requiſite in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to our obtaining Heaven. <hi>Thoſe who by patient continuance in well-doing, ſeek for Glory, Honour, and Immortali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:62862:31" rendition="simple:additions"/>ſhall partake of Eternal Life.</hi> Now were there no other Reaſon of this Conſtitution, but the ſovereign Will of God, it were ſufficient. But the Foundation of it is laid in the nature of the Things themſelves. Therefore our Saviour does not ſimply declare, that an unregenerate Perſon <hi>ſhall not ſee the Kingdom of God,</hi> but with the greateſt emphaſis <hi>cannot,</hi> to ſignify an abſolute impoſſibility of it. Beſides the Legal Bar that excludes unſanctified Perſons from the beatifick viſion of God, there is a moral incapacity. Suppoſe that Juſtice ſhould allow Omnipotence to tranſlate ſuch a Sinner to Heaven, would the Place make him happy? Can two incongruous Natures delight in one another? The Happineſs of Senſe is by an impreſſion of Pleaſure from a ſuitable Object: The Happineſs of intellectual Beings ariſes from an en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tire conformity of diſpoſitions. So that unleſs God recede from his Holineſs, which is abſolutely impoſſible, or Man be purified, and changed into his like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:62862:31" rendition="simple:additions"/>there can be no ſweet Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on between them. Our Saviour aſſigns this Reaſon of the neceſſity of Rege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration in order to our admiſſion in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Heaven: <hi>That which is born of the fleſh, is fleſh; and that which is born of the Spirit, is ſpirit.</hi> According to the quality of the Principle, ſuch is what proceeds from it. The Fleſh is a cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt Principle, and accordingly the natural Man is wholly carnal in his Propenſions, Operations, and End. The Diſeaſe is turn'd into his Conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. He is dead to the Spiritual Life, to the Actions and Enjoyments that are proper to it: Nay, there is in him a ſurviving Principle of Enmity to that Life: not only a mortal coldneſs to God, but a ſtiff averſion from him, a perpetual reſiſtance and impatience of the Divine Preſence, that would diſturb his voluptuous enjoyments. The Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſes of Heaven would be as the Tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of Hell to him, while in the midſt of thoſe pure Joys his inward inclinations vehemently run into the
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:62862:32"/>loweſt Lees of Senſuality. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore till this contrariety, ſo deep and predominant in an unholy PerſOn, be removed, 'tis utterly impoſſible he ſhould enjoy God with ſatisfaction. Holineſs alone prepares Men for the poſſeſſion of Celeſtial Happineſs, that is againſt the corruption, and above the perfection of meer Nature.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Let us then, having ſuch a Joy ſet be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore us, lay aſide every weight, and the Sin which doth ſo eaſily beſet us, and run with patience the race that is ſet be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore us, looking to Jeſus, the Author and Finiſher of our Faith.</hi> Methinks the ſight of worldly Men, ſo active and vigilant to proſecute their low Deſigns, ſhould quicken us to ſeek with the greater diligence and alacrity the <hi>Kingdom of Heaven, and the Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs thereof.</hi> A carnal Wretch ur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged by the ſting of a brutiſh deſire, with what impatience does he purſue <hi>the pleaſure of Sin, which is but for a ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon?</hi> An Ambitious Perſon, with what an intemperate height of Paſſion does
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:62862:32" rendition="simple:additions"/>he chaſe a Feather? A Covetous Man, how greedily does he proſecute the Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantages of the <hi>preſent World that paſſes away,</hi> and the Luſts thereof? Ah! how do they upbraid our indifferent deſires, or dull delays, and cold endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours, when <hi>ſuch an high Prize</hi> is ſet before us? Who is able to conceive the exceſs of Pleaſure the Soul feels when it firſt enters through the beauti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Gate of Paradiſe, and ſees before it that incomprehenſible Glory, and hears a Voice from Him that ſits upon the Throne, <hi>Enter into thy Maſter's Joy,</hi> for ever to be happy with him? The ſerious belief of this will draw forth all our active Powers in the Service of God. The feeding by lively thoughts on this ſupernatural Food, will add new vigor and luſtre to our Graces, and make our Victory eaſy over the World. If we believe indeed that our Bodies ſhall be ſpiritual, and our Souls divine in their perfections, it will make us reſolute to ſubdue the Reble Fleſh, and reſcue the captiv'd Spirit from all
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:62862:33" rendition="simple:additions"/>Intanglements of Iniquity. <hi>Having the promiſe of ſuch an excellent Reward, let us always abound in the Work of the Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. The lively hope of this Bleſſed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs is powerful to ſupport us under the greateſt Troubles can befal us in this our mortal condition. Here we are toſt upon the alternate waves of Time, but hereafter we ſhall arrive at the Port, the bleſſed Boſom of our Saviour, and enjoy a peaceful calm: <hi>and ſo we ſhall ever be with the Lord.</hi> Words of infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite ſweetneſs! This is the Song of our Proſperity, and Charm of our Adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity: <hi>We ſhall ever be with the Lord.</hi> Well might the Apoſtle add immediate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly after, <hi>therefore comfort one another with theſe words.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>More particularly. They are a Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitive to moderate our Sorrows upon the departure of our deareſt Friends, who die in the Lord: for they aſcend from this Valley of Tears, to the hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py Land of the Living. What Father is ſo deſerted of Reaſon, as to bear
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:62862:33" rendition="simple:additions"/>impatiently the parting with his Son, that goes over a narrow part of the Sea, to a rich and pleaſant Country, and receives the inveſtiture and peaceable poſſeſſion of a Kingdom? Nay, by how much the ſtronger his Love is, ſo much the more tranſporting is his Joy: eſpecially if he expects ſhortly to be with him, to ſee him on the Throne, in the ſtate of a King, and to partake of his happineſs. If then it be impoſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to Nature to be grieved at the feli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city of one that is loved; according to what Principle of Nature or Faith do Believers ſo uncomfortably lament the Death of Friends, of whom they have aſſurance that after their leaving our Earth, they enter into an everlaſting Kingdom, to receive a Crown of Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry from Chriſt himſelf? Our Saviour tells the Diſciples, <hi>If ye loved me, ye would rejoyce, becauſe I ſaid I go to my Father,</hi> to ſit down at his right-hand in Majeſty. A pure Affection directly terminates in the happineſs and exalta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Perſon that is loved. I am
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:62862:34" rendition="simple:additions"/>not ſpeaking againſt the exerciſe of ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Affections on the loſs of our dear Friends; and the penſive feeling of God's hand in it; which is a natural and neceſſary duty. There is a great difference betwen Stupidity and Pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence: but violent Paſſion, or unre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting Sorrow, is moſt unbecoming the <hi>bleſſed Hope</hi> aſſur'd to us in the Goſpel.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi> treating of this Argument, and reflecting upon the cuſtom of thoſe Times, wherein at Funeral Solemnities a train of Mourning Women attended the Corps, tearing their Hair and Face, and crying out with all the expreſſions of deſperate Sorrow, breaks forth, <hi>Ah Chriſtian Faith and Religion! that was triumphant over thine Enemies in ſo many Battels and Victories by the Blood and Death of the Martyrs, how art thou contradicted by the practice of theſe who profeſs thee in words? Is this not to be ſorrowful as thoſe that have no hope? Are theſe the affections, the expreſſions of one that believes the bleſſedneſs of Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortal
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:62862:34" rendition="simple:additions"/>Life? What will the Heathens ſay? How will they be induc'd to believe the Promiſes of Chriſt to his Servants of a glorious Kingdom, when thoſe who are ſo in title, behave themſelves as if they had no ſtedfast Faith in them?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. The hopes of this bleſſed ſtate, is able to free us from the fear of Death. This laſt Enemy gives a hot Alarm to Mankind, both as it deprives them of all that is pleaſant here, and for the terrible conſequences that attend it. To the Eye of Senſe, a dead Body is a ſpectacle of fearful appearance. He that a little before heard, and diſcours'd, and with a chearful Air convers'd and enjoy'd the World, now is dead, and all his Senſes in him: the Eyes are dead to light, and the Ears to ſounds, the Tongue to words, the Heart to feel any affections, and the Countenance to diſcover them: nothing remains but ſilence, horrour, and corruption. Beſides, <hi>after Death comes Judgment,</hi> and a ſtate of unrelenting Torments to the wicked. But a true Believer that has been obedient to his
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:62862:35" rendition="simple:additions"/>Saviour, ſees things by another Light than that of ſenſe, and has living hopes in his dying Agonies. He knows that Death to the Saints is but a ſleep: and while the Body reſts in the Grave, the Soul is as it were all Act, continually exerciſing its moſt noble faculties on the beſt Objects. Does the Soul ſleep in that all-enlightned World, that ſees with open face the infinite Beauty of God? that hears and bears a part in the Hymns of the Angels and Saints en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>circling his Throne? that drinks of the Rivers of Pleaſure that flow from his Preſence? that freely and joyfully con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſes with all the Celeſtial Courtiers, the Princes of that Kingdom, the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vourites of God? Then it truly lives. This reconciles Death to a Chriſtian, who has nothing more in his wiſhes than to be with Chriſt, and knows that Diſeaſes and Pains, the fore-run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners of it, are but as breaking down the Walls of this earthly dark Priſon, that the Soul may take its flight to the hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py Region, and for ever enjoy the Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:62862:35"/>of the Sons of God. And for his Body, that ſhall be re-united to the Soul in Glory. Methinks God ſpeaks to a dying Believer, as he did to <hi>Jacob,</hi> when he was to deſcend to <hi>Egypt; Fear not to go down into the Grave, I will go down with thee, and I will bring thee up again.</hi> The ſame Almighty Voice that gave being to the World, ſhall <hi>awake thoſe who ſleep in the Duſt,</hi> and reform them according to the Example of Chriſt's glorified Body. O how ſhould we long for that triumphant day! and with moſt ardent Aſpirings pray, <hi>Thy Kingdom come in its full power and glory?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I Shall now come to ſpeak of the Mournful Subject, the Cauſe of my Appearing here at this time, the Deceaſed, Reverend and Excellent Divine, Dr. <hi>Thomas Manton:</hi> A Name worthy of precious and eternal Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory. And I ſhall conſider him, both in the quality of his Office, as he was an <hi>Embaſſador of Chriſt,</hi> declaring his
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:62862:36"/>Mind, and repreſenting his Authority, and in the holineſs of his Perſon, ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing forth the Graces and Vertues of his Divine Maſter.</p>
            <p>God had furniſh'd him with a rare union of thoſe parts that are requiſite to form an excellent Miniſter of his Word. A clear Judgment, rich Fancy, ſtrong Memory, and happy Elocution met in him, and were excellently im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved by his diligent ſtudy.</p>
            <p>The Preaching of the Word is the principal part of the Miniſter's Duty, moſt eſſential to his Calling, and moſt neceſſary to the Church. For this end chiefly, the ſeverral Orders in the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſterial Office were inſtituted, (<hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4.) and upon our Saviour's triumphant aſcent and reception into Heaven, an abundant effuſion of the Spirit in Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and Abilities deſcended upon Men. Now in the performing this Work, he was of that conſpicuous Eminence, that none could detract from him, but from ignorance or envy.</p>
            <p>He was endowed with extraordinary
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:62862:36"/>knowledg in the Scriptures, thoſe Holy Oracles from whence all Spiritual Light is derived: And in his preaching, gave ſuch a perſpicuous account of the order and dependence of Divine Truths; and with that felicity applied the Scriptures to confirm them, that every Subject by his management was culti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vated and improved. His Diſcourſes were ſo clear and convincing, that none without offering voluntary vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence to Conſcience, could reſiſt their Evidence. And from hence they were effectual not only to inſpire a ſudden Flame, and raiſe a ſhort Commotion in the Affections, but to make a laſting Change in the Life. For in the hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Soul ſuch is the compoſition of its Faculties, that till the Underſtanding be rectified in its Apprehenſions and Eſtimations, the Will is never induc'd to make an entire firm choice of what is neceſſary for the obtaining perfect Happineſs. A ſincere perſevering Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion is effected by weighty Reaſons, that ſink and ſettle in the Heart.</p>
            <pb n="68" facs="tcp:62862:37" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>His Doctrine was uncorrupt and pure, <hi>the Truth according to Godlineſs.</hi> He was far from a guilty vile intention, to proſtitute that ſacred Ordinance for the acquiring any private ſecular ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage. Neither did he entertain his Hearers with impertinent Subtilties, empty Notions, intricate Diſputes, dry and barren without productive Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue: But as one that always had before his Eyes the great End of the Miniſtry, the Glory of God, and the Salvation of Men, his Sermons were directed to open their eyes, that they might ſee their wretched condition as Sinners, to haſten their <hi>flight from the Wrath to come,</hi> to make them humbly, thankful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and entirely <hi>receive Chriſt,</hi> as their <hi>Prince,</hi> and <hi>all-ſufficient Saviour.</hi> And to build up the Converted <hi>in their moſt holy Faith,</hi> and more excellent Love, that is <hi>the fulfilling of the Law.</hi> In ſhort, to make true Chriſtians emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent in Knowledg and Univerſal Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience.</p>
            <p>As the Matter of his Sermons was
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:62862:37" rendition="simple:additions"/>deſigned for the good of Souls; ſo his way of expreſſion was proper to that end. Words are the Vehicle of the Heavenly Light. As the Divine Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom was incarnate to reveal the Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Counſels of God to the World; ſo Spiritual Wiſdom in the Mind, muſt be clothed with words, to make it ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible to others. And in this he had a ſingular Talent. His Stile was not exquiſitely ſtudied, not conſiſting of harmonious Periods, but far diſtant from vulgar meanneſs. His Expreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on was natural and free, clear and elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent, quick and powerful, without any ſpice of folly, and always ſuitable to the Simplicity and Majeſty of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Truths. His Sermons afforded ſubſtantial food with delight, ſo that a faſtidious Mind could not diſreliſh them. He abhorr'd a vain oſtentation of Wit, in handling Sacred things; ſo venerable and grave, and of eternal conſequence. Indeed, what is more unbecoming a Miniſter of Chriſt, than to waſte the ſpirits of his Brain, as a
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:62862:38" rendition="simple:additions"/>Spider does his bowels, to ſpin a Web only to catch Flies? to get vain ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plauſe by fooliſh pleaſing the ignorant. And what cruelty is it to the Souls of Men?<note place="margin">Suet.</note> 'Tis recorded as an inſtance of <hi>Nero</hi>'s ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vage temper, that in a general Famine, when many periſh'd by hunger, he or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered a Ship ſhould come from <hi>Egypt</hi> (the Granary of <hi>Italy</hi>) laden with Sand for the uſe of Wreſtlers. In ſuch extremity to provide only for delight, that there might be Spectacles on the Theatre, when the City of <hi>Rome</hi> was a ſpectacle of ſuch miſery, as to melt the heart of any but a <hi>Nero,</hi> was moſt barbarous Cruelty. But 'tis cruelty of an heavier imputation, for a Miniſter to prepare his Sermons to pleaſe the fooliſh curioſity of Fancy with flaſhy Conceits; nay, ſuch light Vanities, that would ſcarce be endured in a Scene, whiles hungry Souls languiſh for want of ſolid nouriſhment.</p>
            <p>His fervour and earneſtneſs in Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing was ſuch, as might ſoften and make
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:62862:38"/>pliant the moſt ſtubborn, obdurate Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits. I am not ſpeaking of one whoſe Talent was only in Voice, that labours in the Pulpit as if the end of Preaching were for the exerciſe of the Body,<note place="margin">Si ſudare ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter non potes, eſt alind.</note> and not for the profit of Souls: But this <hi>Man of God</hi> was inflam'd with an Holy Zeal, and from thence ſuch ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent expreſſions broke forth, as were capable to procure attention and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent in his Hearers. He ſpake as one that had a living Faith within him of Divine Truths. From this union of Zeal with his Knowledg, he was ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellently qualified to convince and convert Souls. The ſound of words only ſtrikes the Ear, but the Mind rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons with the Mind, and the Heart ſpeaks to the Heart.</p>
            <p>His unparallel'd Aſſiduity in Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, declar'd him very ſenſible of thoſe dear and ſtrong Obligations that lie upon Miniſters, to be very diligent in that Bleſſed Work. What a powerful
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:62862:39" rendition="simple:additions"/>Motive our Saviour urged upon St. <hi>Peter?</hi>
               <note place="margin">John <hi>21.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>As thou lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veſt me, feed my Sheep, feed my Lambs.</hi> And can any feed too much, when none can love enough? Can any Pains be ſufficient for the Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of Souls, for which the Son of God did not eſteem his Blood too coſtly a price? Is not inceſſant unwea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried Induſtry requiſite to advance the Work of Grace in them to perfection? In this the Work of a Miniſter has its peculiar diſadvantage, That whereas an Artificer, how curious and difficult ſoever his Work be, yet has this en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragement, That what is begun with Art and Care, he finds in the ſame ſtate wherein 'twas left. A Painter that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigns an exact Piece, draws many Lines, often touches it with his Pencil to give it Life and Beauty, and though unfiniſh'd, 'tis not ſpoil'd by his inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion. A Sculptor that carves a Statue, though his labour be hard from the reſiſtance of the Matter, yet his Work remains firm and durable. But
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:62862:39" rendition="simple:additions"/>the Heart of Man is of a ſtrange tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, hard as Marble, not eaſily recep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive of Heavenly Impreſſions; yet fluid as Water, thoſe Impreſſions are eaſily defac'd in it; 'tis expos'd to ſo many temptations that induce an oblivion of eternal things, that without frequent excitations to quicken and confirm its holy purpoſes, it grows careleſs, and all the labour is loſt that was ſpent on it. This faithful Miniſter <hi>abounded in the Work of the Lord;</hi> and which is truly admirable, though ſo frequent in Preaching, yet was always ſuperior to others, and equal to himſelf. In his laſt time when declining to Death, yet he would not leave his beloved Work; the vigour of his Mind ſupporting the weakneſs of his Body. I remember when oppreſt with an obſtinate Hoarſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, a Friend deſiring him to ſpare himſelf; he rejected the advice with indignation.</p>
            <p>He was no fomenter of Faction but ſtudious of the Publick Tranquillity. He knew what a Bleſſing Peace is, and
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:62862:40" rendition="simple:additions"/>wiſely foreſaw the pernicious Conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quences that attend Diviſions. By Peace, the bond of mutual Harmony, the weakeſt things are preſerv'd and proſper; but where Diſcord reigns, the ſtrongeſt are near to ruin. The heavenly Conſent in the Primitive Church, was a principal cauſe of its miraculous increaſe and flouriſhing; but after Diſſentions prevail'd amongſt Chriſtians, that was deſtroy'd in a ſhort time, which was built by the Divine Union and Heroick Patience of the Primitive Chriſtians. And the glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Beginnings that promis'd the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation of all <hi>Europe,</hi> were more ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed by the Diſſentions of ſome employed in that Bleſſed Work, than by all the Power and Subtilty, the Arms and Artifices of <hi>Rome</hi> it ſelf. How afflictive is the conſideration of our divided Church? Sweet Peace! whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther art thou fled? Bleſſed Saviour! who didſt by thy precious Blood re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>concile Heaven and Earth, ſend down thy Spirit to inſpire us with that Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:62862:40" rendition="simple:additions"/>that is pure and peaceable, that thoſe who agree in the ſame Principles of Faith, in the ſame ſubſtantial parts of Worſhip, in aſſerting the ſame indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpenſible neceſſity of Holineſs, may receive one another in love. I am affectionately engaged in a Matter that ſo nearly touches all thoſe that value the <hi>Proteſtant</hi> Intereſt.</p>
            <p>Briefly; Conſider him as a <hi>Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an,</hi> his Life was anſwerable to his Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine.</p>
            <p>'Tis applicable to ſome Miniſters, what is obſerved of the Carbuncle; by its colour, luſtre, and fiery ſparklings it ſeems to be actually a Fire, but it has only the name and appearance of it. Thus ſome in the Pulpit ſeem to be all on fire with Zeal, yet their Hearts are as cold as a Stone, without Holy Affections, and their Lives are unwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy their Divine Miniſtration. But this Servant of God was like a fruitful Tree, that produces in its Branches what it contains in the Root; his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Grace was made viſible in a
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:62862:41"/>Converſation becoming the Goſpel of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>His reſolute Contempt of the World ſecur'd him from being wrought on by thoſe Motives, that tempt low Spirits from their Duty. He would not raſhly throw himſelf into troubles, nor <hi>ſpretâ Conſcientiâ</hi> avoid them. His generous Conſtancy of Mind in reſiſting the current of Popular Humour, declar'd his Loyalty to his Divine Maſter. His Charity was eminent in procuring Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plies for others, when in mean Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances himſelf. But he had great experience of God's fatherly Proviſion, to which his filial Confidence was cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſpondent.</p>
            <p>His Converſation in his Family was holy and exemplary, every day in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructing them from the Scriptures in their Duty.</p>
            <p>I ſhall finiſh my Character of him, with obſerving his Humility. He was deeply affected with the ſenſe of his Frailties and Unworthineſs. He con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered the infinite Purity of God, the
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:62862:41"/>Perfection of his Law the Rule of our Duty, and by that humbling Light diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover'd his manifold defects. He ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſt his thoughts to me a little before his Death; <hi>If the Holy Prophets were under ſtrong impreſſions of fear, upon the extraordinary diſcovery of the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Preſence, how ſhall we poor Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures appear before that Holy and Dread Majeſty? Iſaiah,</hi> after his glorious viſion of God, reflecting upon him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, as not retir'd from the commerce and corruption of the World, breaks forth, <hi>Wo is me, for I am undone! be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe I am a Man of unclean Lips, and I dwell in the midſt of a People of un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clean Lips; for mine Eyes have ſeen the King, the Lord of Hoſts.</hi> 'Tis infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitely terrible to appear <hi>before God the Judg of all,</hi> without the protection of <hi>the Blood of Sprinkling, that ſpeaks bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter things than the Blood of Abel.</hi> This alone reliev'd him, and ſupported his hopes. Though his Labours were a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundant, yet he knew that the Work of God, paſſing through our hands, is
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:62862:42"/>ſo blemiſh'd, that without an appeal to pardoning Mercy and Grace, we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſtand in Judgment. This was the Subject of his laſt publick Sermon.</p>
            <p>He languiſh'd many months, but preſuming he ſhould be too ſtrong for his Infirmity, neglected it, till at laſt it became inſuperable and mortal. Many pathetical aggravations heighten our great and dear Loſs; That ſuch a faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Miniſter of Chriſt ſhould be taken away, whoſe Preaching was ſo power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful to repair the woful Ruins of Godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and Virtue in a degenerate Age: Whoſe prudent pacifick Spirit rendred him ſo uſeful in theſe <hi>Divided Times,</hi> when Profeſſors of the ſame Religion are alienated from one another, as if they had been baptized with the Waters of Strife: That before our Tears were dried up for the loſs of other worthy Miniſters, the Fountain of Sorrow ſhould be opened again by this afflict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſtroke. But it becomes us to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the Diſpenſations of Heaven with
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:62862:42" rendition="simple:additions"/>humble and quiet ſubmiſſion; to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flect upon our ſins with an holy grief, that provoke God to remove ſuch an excellent Inſtrument of his Glory from us. <hi>Let us pray to the Lord of the Harveſt, that he will ſend forth Faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Labourers into it.</hi> O that ſurviving Miniſters might be animated with a Zeal more pure and fervent in their Divine Work! And that People would be wiſe, while a price is put into their hands, to improve it for their eternal advantage. The neglected Goſpel will at laſt be a terrible Witneſs againſt the Diſobedient, to juſtifie and aggravate their Condemnation.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:62862:43"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:62862:43"/>
            <head>Dr. Manton's LAST SERMON ON 2 TIM 1.18.</head>
            <pb facs="tcp:62862:44"/>
            <pb n="83" facs="tcp:62862:44"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>2 TIM. 1.18.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>The Lord grant unto him that he may find Mercy of the Lord in that day.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>THE Words are the Apoſtle's Prayer for <hi>Oneſiphorus.</hi> He prays for his Houſhold, <hi>v.</hi> 16, <hi>The Lord give mercy to the Houſe of Oneſiphorus.</hi> His Family was probably now at <hi>Epheſus,</hi> the ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry place of his Abode, where <hi>Timothy</hi> alſo was, to whom he wrote; but he himſelf was then at <hi>Rome.</hi> Secondly, He prays for his Perſon, in the Text. That which put him upon theſe Prayers was the Kindneſs he had received of him at <hi>Epheſus,</hi> and afterwards at <hi>Rome; where he ſought him, and found him out, and was not afraid to own him, and relieve him, nor aſhamed of his Chain.</hi>
               <pb n="84" facs="tcp:62862:45" rendition="simple:additions"/>In requital, he prayeth God to be his Paymaſter, and to return his Kindneſs into his boſom. He ſhewed mercy to <hi>Paul,</hi> and therefore <hi>Paul</hi> deſired the Lord to ſhew him mercy. He ſeeking <hi>Paul,</hi> found him; ſo he deſireth God would <hi>let him find mercy. Paul</hi> found mercy of him in a Priſon, let him find it in Paradiſe. <hi>The Lord grant unto him, that he may find Mercy of the Lord in that day.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the Words three things are to be obſerved.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. The Perſon, for whom he prays.</item>
               <item>2. The Matter, for which he prays.</item>
               <item>3. The Time, when this is to be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſh'd.</item>
            </list>
            <p n="1">1. The Perſon for whom he prays, <hi>Oneſiphorus,</hi> a good Man, <hi>that God would grant to Him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. The Matter for which he prays, <hi>that he may find Mercy of the Lord.</hi> A neceſſary requeſt; for Mercy is the Original and Riſe of all the Recompen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces we expect from God. Mercy be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginneth our Salvation, and Mercy
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:62862:45" rendition="simple:additions"/>crowneth it. Mercy entreth us into the Covenant of Grace, and Mercy conſummateth the Happineſs we have thereby. <hi>Jud.</hi> 21. <hi>Looking for the Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of our Lord Jeſus unto Eternal Life.</hi> We are not only pardoned out of Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, but glorified out of Mercy. A ſuitable Requeſt, for God loves to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taliate, or pay us in kind. <hi>Merciful Men ſhall obtain Mercy,</hi> Mat. 5.7. On the contrary, <hi>Jam.</hi> 2.13. <hi>They ſhall have Judgment without Mercy, who have ſhewed no Mercy.</hi> And as this is ſuitable, ſo it is moſt kindly believed; for we muſe of God as we uſe our ſelves: they that are not faithful to themſelves, and do not keep their own Promiſes, can never be confident in God's. Revengeful Men are moſt apt to diſtruſt of God's pardoning Mercy. Thoſe that are hard and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merciful, and do not pity the miſery of others, do more difficultly believe God's tender Mercies and Compaſſions.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The Time mentioned in the Prayer, <hi>in that Day.</hi> Some ſay, when
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:62862:46" rendition="simple:additions"/>he alſo ſhould be afflicted. Others the Day of Death: but rather the Day of Judgment, that is often called a Day by way of excellency; <hi>Acts</hi> 17.30. <hi>He hath appointed a Day,</hi> &amp;c. 2 Theſſ. 1.10. <hi>When God ſhall come to be glorified in his Saints, and admired in all them that believe. In that Day,</hi> that is, the Day when Chriſt ſhall come to judg the Quick and the Dead, and to diſtribute Puniſhments and Rewards. That is the Day when Mercy ſhall ſtand us in moſt ſtead; and if it go well with us then, it will go well with us for ever.</p>
            <p>Doct. <hi>That the beſt of God's Children will very much need Mercy in the Day of Judgment.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Apoſtle prays for a good Man, who was full of good Fruits, <hi>that he might find Mercy.</hi> Had <hi>Oneſiphorus</hi> need of Mercy, and have not we? Surely the free Mercy of God is our beſt plea at that time.</p>
            <pb n="87" facs="tcp:62862:46" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>I ſhall ſtate this Point.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The Mercy here ſpoken of, doth not exclude and ſhut out the Satisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Chriſt; for God ſhews this Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy as propitiated by Chriſt: for that was the moſt convenient way to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrate his Juſtice and Holineſs, and to vindicate the Honour of his Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment and Law, and to be a war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning to Sinners not to preſume upon his Mercy. Therefore this is called the <hi>Mercy of our Lord Jeſus Christ,</hi> Jud. 21. Our Eternal Bleſſedneſs is the Fruit of his Merit and Satisfaction.</p>
            <p n="2">2. This Mercy muſt not be urged to exclude our Qualification: for, till we are qualified, we have no right to the good things of the Covenant. The Mercy and Favour of God is conditio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal, but yet free; not due by any Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit and Claim, but that of his Promiſe; and his Promiſe is made to them that are rightly qualified, the ſincere Belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, the Holy, the Humble, and the Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitent; others are uncapable of Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy. You muſt not think God will
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:62862:47"/>ſhew Mercy to Men, though they have no inherent Holineſs at all. Faith and Repentance are requir'd before we can be pardoned.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Though Mercy be our beſt Plea; yet you muſt not take it ſo, as if a Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liever's Condition were doubtful and uncertain, and a good Chriſtian could not know how it will fare with him. The Mercy of the Lord is the Ground of our Hope, but in conjunction with other Evidences, whereby they under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand their Eſtate. The moſt ſerious People do conſider the weight of the Matter; but Humility is not Uncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainty. They are unworthy in the bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken-hearted ſenſe of their own Defects and Failings; but God counteth them worthy, becauſe of their Diligence and Seriouſneſs in the Heavenly Life. <hi>Luk.</hi> 21.35. <hi>Watch ye therefore, and pray always, that ye may be counted wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy.</hi> He accepteth them as worth; <hi>They ſhall walk with me in white, for they are worthy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. God's Servants <hi>plead Sincerity</hi> though
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:62862:47" rendition="simple:additions"/>not a finleſs ſpotleſs State. Perfect Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs according to the Covenant of Works they cannot plead; but ſincere Righteouſneſs according to the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of Grace, they may and do plead. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 38.3. <hi>Remember, O Lord, I beſeech thee, how I have walked before thee in Truth, and with a perfect Heart.</hi> Their Graces and Duties will endure the Touchſtone, though not the Ballance; are of the right kind, though not full weight. There muſt be inherent Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs, or you will never come to Glory.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Though they may take Comfort in their Evidences, yet they dare not plead the Merit of any thing in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves. They take comfort in their Evidences; 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.12. <hi>For our rejoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing is the Teſtimony of our Conſcience; that in Simplicity and godly Sincerity, we have had our Converſation in the World.</hi> They are God's, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.94. <hi>I am thine, ſave me.</hi> Yet they dare not challenge God's Reward as a a Debt. If God ſhould deal with them accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:62862:48" rendition="simple:additions"/>to their Deſervings, their very Rem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of Sins were enough to bring them to Damnation; yea they would not be an hour out of Hell, aſſoon as God ſhould enter his Action againſt them.</p>
            <p n="6">6. Though they are not perfect, yet they are not wicked; there is enough to difference the Godly from the Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly. <hi>Job</hi> 10.7. <hi>Thou knowest I am not wicked.</hi> Though all Men be Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, yet ſome have eſcaped the Reign of Sin. We muſt diſtinguiſh our ſelves. 1 <hi>John</hi> 3.10. <hi>In this the Children of God are manifeſted, and the Children of the Devil; whoſoever doth not Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, is not of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Many Arguments will ſhew the Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity of this.</p>
            <p>Firſt, From the Nature of God. who is a God of exact Purity, glorious Majeſty, impartial Juſtice, and infinite Knowledge. All which ſhew the need of Mercy.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The Holy Nature of God. When he is upon his Judicial Proceſs here in the World, who is able to endure
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:62862:48"/>it? The Men of <hi>Bethſhemeſh</hi> ſaid, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 6. <hi>Who is able to ſtand before this Holy Lord God?</hi> That is, becauſe he ſhews himſelf ſo Zealous of his Inſtitutions. And, <hi>Joſh.</hi> 24.19. <hi>Ye cannot ſerve the Lord, for he is a Holy God.</hi> He ſpeaks not this to diſcourage them, but that they might not have ſlight thoughts of God, and his Service, as if he did make little reckoning of Sin, or that it were not ſo hateful to him, and ſo great a Matter as uſually it is made to be. Slight Spirits wonder why Men make ſuch ado about Sin. What harm is it, ſay they, to take a little forbidden Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, or to indulge a wanton Thought, or drop a vain Word? Theſe Men are ignorant of the Purity and Holineſs of God; therefore their Humiliation and Repentance is thought needleſs, their Senſe of the Neceſſity and Bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit of Pardon leſſen'd, their Awe and Watchfulneſs abated. What thoughts they have of Sin, the ſame they think God hath. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 50.21. <hi>Thou thoughteſt I was altogether ſuch an one as thy ſelf.</hi>
               <pb n="92" facs="tcp:62862:49" rendition="simple:additions"/>They make light work of Sin, either in repenting, or watching and ſtriving againſt it. Certainly, they that have ſlight thoughts of Sin, never have great thoughts of God. If we think ſeriouſly of the Purity and Holineſs of God, it would be another Matter, and it would not ſo lightly go off the Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence.</p>
            <p n="2">2. There is the glorious Majeſty of God. He is a Sovereign, and all his Recompences are Acts of Grace, and not of Debt. <hi>Job</hi> ſaith, (<hi>Job.</hi> 19.15.) <hi>Though I were righteous, I would not an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer; but I would make Supplication to my Judge.</hi> Whatever Senſe we have of our own Integrity, and the Good wrought in us, yet Supplications for Mercy do become the Creature. For God is our Sovereign, and repreſented there as our Supreme Judge, whoſe Tribunal none can decline, whoſe Exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination and Trial is moſt ſtrict and accurate, whoſe Doom and Sentence is deciſive and abſolute, without power of appealing or repealing; and the Exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:62862:49" rendition="simple:additions"/>and Puniſhment moſt dreadful. Therefore nothing becomes us ſo much as a broken-hearted Imploring of Grace and Mercy. God is ſo great and glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, that we can merit nothing at his hands; all that is done to us muſt be meer Grace. This is the Difference between Sin and Obedience: the Hei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nouſneſs of Sin is always aggravated by the greatneſs of the Object againſt whom it is committed; but the Value of Obedience is ſtill thereby leſſened. The Offence is aggravated. To ſtrike an Officer, is more than to ſtrike a private Man, a King more than an ordinary Officer: ſo the Infinite Majeſty of God greatens the Offence. But on the other ſide, the greater God is, and the more glorious, the more it leſſens the Value of that Good we perform. We can never oblige him. <hi>When we have done all that ever we can, we are but unprofitable Servants,</hi> Luk. 17.10. Mercy is the Fountain of all that we are and hope for. That Grace which firſt accepted us with all our Faults, doth at laſt crown us.</p>
            <pb n="94" facs="tcp:62862:50"/>
            <p n="3">3. The Impartial Juſtice of God. That belongs to him, as Governour of the World. There is a threefold Juſtice in God.</p>
            <p n="1">(1.) His general Juſtice. That re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires, <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>t bonis benè ſit, &amp; malis malè;</hi> That it ſhould be well with them that do well, and ill with them that do ill. This is ſpoken of, 2 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 1.6, 7. <hi>It is a righteous thing with God to render Tribulation unto them that trouble you, and unto you that are troubled, Rest.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">(2.) His ſtrict Juſtice, according to the Covenant of Works. If God ſhould deal with us according to our undeſervings and ill-deſervings, not in a way of gracious Compaſſion, what would become of the beſt of Men in the World? Not one of us could ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear in Court. For there is not a Man found, that hath not ſome Fault and Failing, which would render him un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>capable of God's Favour. If he ſhould proceed in juſt Severity againſt us, who could ſtand? not only who among the wicked, but who among the People of
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:62862:50" rendition="simple:additions"/>God? <hi>Pſal.</hi> 130.14. Therefore that Judgment muſt be deprecated, as <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi> doth, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 143.2. <hi>Enter <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>t into Judgment with thy Servant, for in thy ſight ſhall no Man living be juſtified.</hi> It is impoſſible for ſuch a frail ſinful Creature as Man is, to appear before God's exact Tribunal with any Comfort and Hope. Now becauſe this ſtrict Juſtice of God leaves us in ſuch a deſperate and hope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs Condition, there is another Court ſet up, to which we may appeal, even the Covenant of Grace, which allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth Pardon to penitent and ſincere Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers.</p>
            <p n="3">(3.) There is his merciful Juſtice, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to Promiſe in the new Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant. <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.10. <hi>God is not unrighte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, to forget the Work and Labour of Love.</hi> 1 John 1.9. <hi>He is faithful and just to forgive us our Sins, and to cleanſe us from all <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nrighteouſneſs.</hi> Not that the Work deſerveth his Grace, but God having made himſelf a Debtor by his own Promiſe, it is juſt that he ſhould make it good. Now this is the
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:62862:51" rendition="simple:additions"/>ſame we ſpeak of in the Text, <hi>The Lord grant that he may find Mercy in that Day <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> It is his Grace to enable us to perform the Condition, and it is his merciful Juſtice to accept of it, when it is performed.</p>
            <p n="4">4. His Infinite Knowledge, by which he takes notice of all that we do. We may be blinded with Partiality and Self-love, but the Holy and All-ſeeing God knows many Faults, which Men either cannot or will not ſee; 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.9. <hi>I know nothing of my ſelf, yet am I not hereby justified.</hi> Some of God's People have attain'd to new Covenant-Righteouſneſs, yet they dare not ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture their Eternal Eſtate upon that alone. Suppoſe our Hearts condemn us in part, we know ſomewhat by our ſelves, yet God knoweth more. 1 <hi>John</hi> 3.20. <hi>For if our Hearts condemn us, God is greater than our Hearts, and knows all thins.</hi> Things appear other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe to the Holy God, than they do to us. <hi>Luk.</hi> 16.15. <hi>And he ſaid unto them, Ye are they who justify your ſelves
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:62862:51" rendition="simple:additions"/>before Men, but God knoweth their Hearts, for that which is highly eſteemed among Men, is an Abomination in the ſight of God.</hi> God many times deteſts that which is highly valued and cried up in the World. So <hi>Prov.</hi> 16.2. <hi>All the ways of Man are clean in his own eyes, but the Lord weighs the Spirits.</hi> We look to the Bulk and Matter of the Action, but God looks to the Mind and Spirit with which it is performed. We look to the Action ſlightly, ſo as to overlook the Evil that is in it through partiality and indulgence to our ſelves; but God exactly weighs things, and puts them into the Ballance of the Sanctua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry: Therefore we ſee a neceſſity, that when we come into the preſence of the Righteous and Impartial Judg of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven and Earth, we ſhould make Mercy our Plea; though we be conſcious of no Defect and Diſobedience, ſaw no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, or knew nothing amiſs by our ſelves, yet God knows Failings, ſees Errors. Job 9.22. <hi>If I were perfect, yet do I not know my own Soul.</hi> That is,
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:62862:52" rendition="simple:additions"/>I would not go by the inward ſenſe and feeling of my Conſcience, but give up the Cauſe to God, that he might juſtly condemn me: for no Man ſees exactly the depth of his own Heart; therefore I would not argue my Right, but crave Mercy: So that you ſee it is Mercy that muſt ſtand us in moſt ſtead.</p>
            <p n="2">2. From the Condition and Diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition of the Saints.</p>
            <p n="1">(1.) Their Condition; they were once Sinners, and ſtill are imperfect. Once Sinners, liable to the Wrath of God. And as they were once Sinners, they are ſtill to own the Merit of Sin, though not to determine the Event: for <hi>they are to judg themſelves,</hi> 1 Cor. 11.31. Though they are as Brands pluckt out of the Burning, yet they deſerv'd the Burning. I do not tell you what God will do, but what you have deſerved; not to weaken your confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence &amp; rejoycing in <hi>Chriſt,</hi> but to hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble your Hearts. You had once the Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence paſt upon you, and had the Rope
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:62862:52" rendition="simple:additions"/>about your Necks; you were at the Gates of Hell, and might have entred in, but for the Grace of your Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemer. A ſenſe of it is ſtill neceſſary to quicken your Thankfulneſs and Prayers for Mercy and Pardon, and to promote your Humility. You turn Grace into Wantonneſs, and abuſe it, if it leſſen any of theſe Acts: for though God forgive, we muſt not for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get. We were once as bad as the worſt, <hi>and Children of Wrath even as others,</hi> Epheſ. 2.3. Therefore when God ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifies us, we muſt ſtill condemn our ſelves. We are ſtill imperfect, and the beſt feel and find in themſelves great Infirmities, and make but too much work for pardoning Mercy. There are great mixtures of Sin that we are conſcious unto, notwithſtanding the little good which we perform. <hi>Job</hi> 9.2, 3. <hi>How ſhould Man be juſt with God? If he ſhould contend with him, he cannot anſwer one of a thouſand.</hi> Our Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs is ſo imperfect and full of De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects,
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:62862:53"/>that we do not make it our Plea, but God's Mercy is our beſt and ſureſt confidence. There are many ſins that we are conſcious unto; Pſal. 40.11. <hi>Innumerable Evils have compaſſed me about,</hi> therefore what ſhould we do but cry for mercy and forgiveneſs of them? <hi>Lord be merciful to me, a Sinner,</hi> Luke 18.13.</p>
            <p n="3">(2.) The Diſpoſition of the Saints: They have a greater apprehenſion of the Evil of Sin, becauſe of the increaſe of Light and Love: As their Light and Love increaſes, ſo doth their Trouble about Sin. <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.9, 24. <hi>Paul</hi> maketh more complaint about remaining Sins that cleave to the Beſt, than the Wicked do about reigning Luſts. They are aſhamed of the folly and filthineſs that is in Sin, troubled and griev'd for their unkindneſs to God; and therefore are more apprehenſive of the need of Mercy than poſſibly others can be: None ſee ſo many Sins, none ſee ſo much hainouſneſs in Sin. In a clear Glaſs of Water the leaſt Mote is eſpied:
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:62862:53"/>and the moſt delicate and tender Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexions are moſt ſenſible of annoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance. Therefore if God will ſhew mercy to them, notwithſtanding all their unkind dealings with him, they apprehend it as a great and wonderful favour.</p>
            <p n="2">(2.) They have a greater dread of God's Juſtice and Holineſs, and a more ſincere reſpect to the Threatnings of his Word: It is true, they do not fear as before with a Tormenting Fear, yet have a great reverence for the Sentence of his Law, and a more firm belief of his eternal Recompenſes than the blind and ſtupid World hath. Therefore they more earneſtly deprecate his An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, have a greater care to pleaſe him, a more piercing grief, becauſe they have offended him; and therefore if God will ſhew them mercy in the free and full forgiveneſs of all their Offences, they are more apprehenſive of the Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit. They know God's Word is true, and obſerve his Providences as a Comment on it, <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.18. None of
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:62862:54" rendition="simple:additions"/>them can or dare appear in the Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, till they have ſought his Favour, and obtain'd his Pardon.</p>
            <p n="3">(3.) They are more ſollicitous in the Caſe, than others who make a light buſineſs of Salvation, and do the Work of an Age in a Breath. We are all Sinners, but God is merciful. They know that a buſineſs of this weight muſt be carried on with all diligence imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able. Phil. 2.12. <hi>Work out your own Salvation with fear and trembling.</hi> They ſee ſo many deceive themſelves, make a full account they ſhall be ſaved;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rev.</hi> 3.17. <hi>Matth.</hi> 25.</note> do well in the Judgment, when there is no ground for it. They know the ſleightneſs that is incident to humane Nature, the deceit and hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocriſie of their own Hearts; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore uſe diligent Cares, conſtant Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, continual Watchings; and when they have done all, dare not reſt upon that, but the Mercy of Jeſus Chriſt, as their beſt Refuge and Comfort.</p>
            <pb n="103" facs="tcp:62862:54"/>
            <p n="3">3dly. With reſpect to the Purity and Strictneſs of his Law, which is the Rule of Commerce between us and God. The Law may be conſidered, as it re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lateth to the Covenant of Works, or as it relateth to the Covenant of Grace.</p>
            <p n="1">(1.) With reſpect to the Covenant of Works, where the leaſt Failing lays us open to the Curſe, ſurely no Plea can be allowed but Mercy. For that Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant ſhuts up from all Hope of Eſcape, unleſs Mercy opens the Door for us. <hi>Rom.</hi> 11.32. <hi>He hath concluded all under <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nbelief, that he may have Mercy upon all.</hi> Gal. 3.11. <hi>The Scripture concluded all under Sin.</hi> All are guilty of Diſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience unto God, that all might be ſaved by Merey and Grace. 'Tis a Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>militude taken from Malefactors, who are ſhut up in Priſon to be kept unto Puniſhment. For who among us can perfectly keep the Law?</p>
            <p n="2">(2.) With reſpect to the Covenant of Grace; where God requireth Perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, but will accept of Sincerity. The
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:62862:55"/>Law of God is ſtill in force; for it is adopted into the Frame of the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant as the Rule of our Duty. The Rule is as ſtrict as ever, but the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant is not ſo ſtrict. The Rule is as ſtrict, for it ſtill requireth Perfection; but the Covenant is not ſo ſtrict, it is not ſo indiſpenſibly required, becauſe Sincerity, or Perfection of Parts, is ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted inſtead of Perfection of Degrees. Perfection is ſtill required: otherwiſe our Defects were nothing, and we might allow our ſelves in our Failings, and no great Harm would come of it. And then to ſtrive after Perfection, or to <hi>preſs towards the Mark,</hi> would not be a neceſſary Duty, but only a Work of Super-errogation. No; it doth in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vite us to the higheſt Degree of God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs, and makes the Endeavour after Perfection a neceſſary Condition of our Happineſs, as Perfection it ſelf to be our proper Happineſs. And ſo our Duty and Felicity do agree, that we may not have any liberty to be bad and mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable. But yet it accepteth of Sinceri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:62862:55"/>if our Hearts be upright with God, and our whole Mind and Deſire be ſet to obey, pleaſe, and glorify him, and we make it our main Work ſo to do. God will not enter into Judgment with his Servants, nor be ſtrict and ſevere to his Children, nor condemn thoſe that love and fear him for leſſer Failings and Infirmities, nor take that Occaſion to ruine and deſtroy them. Indeed as the new Covenant commandeth Perfection, it noteth our Infirmities, to humble us in order to our Cure. Chriſt, as a Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſician, looks to our Infirmities, to rid us of them, and free us from them; but not as a Judge, to condemn us for them. But yet, becauſe of the multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of our Errors, the holieſt, and humbleſt, and moſt penitent believing Soul is ſcarce able to abide the Trial. Therefore when we have done, our utmoſt Mercy in that Day is our great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt and ſureſt Support.</p>
            <p n="4">4thly. With reſpect to the Day of Judgment.</p>
            <pb n="106" facs="tcp:62862:56" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p n="1">1. The Preparation that is neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry. Since Chriſt is ready to judg, and we know not the Day and Hour of his Coming, we ſhould be ready to be judged. A ſad Meeting and Greeting there will be between Chriſt and an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prepared Soul. Therefore it concerns us deeply, to ſee whether we be ready to give up our Account to God. Now there is a twofold Readineſs; when you are in a ſafe Condition, and when you are in a comfortable Caſe, with reſpect to that Day. All that are in a ſafe Caſe, know not that they are in a comfortable Caſe, know not that it ſhall go well with them in the Judgment. Our Safety is known by the Law of Grace; for Chriſt will judge <hi>according the Goſpel.</hi> Rom. 2.16. Whom the Goſpel doth juſtify, they ſhall be juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied; and whom the Goſpel doth con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn, they ſhall be condemned. The Rules of judging are in the Word, but every one cannot apply them. Now the Goſpel juſtifieth all that repent and believe. By Repentance meaning a
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:62862:56" rendition="simple:additions"/>Turning in Heart and Life to God: and by Faith, a believing what Chriſt hath done for the Reſtauration and Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of Sinners, and an accepting, and making uſe of him to this End. But theſe things are not wrought in us as ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily as they are ſpoken of. And when they are wrought in us, they are not ſo ſoon evidenc'd, that we have Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance unto Life, and Faith unfeign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. Now then, is it not a neceſſary Prayer whilſt we are in the midſt of our Doubts and Conflicts, that we may find Mercy in that day.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The ſtrict Trial that we muſt un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dergo. The Day of Judgment is the greateſt and moſt dreadful Day that ever was, when it is Matter of Senſe, as now it is Matter of Faith. If a Man had it, he would give all the World for Mercy in that Day. For then the Judg will come from <hi>Heaven with a ſhout, and the Books ſhall be opened,</hi> Rev. 10.12. the Book of Conſcience, and the Book of God's Remembrance, and <hi>every thing muſt be produced in the
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:62862:57" rendition="simple:additions"/>Judgment, whether it be Good or Evil,</hi> Eccleſ. 12.14. Now the thought of this ſhould make us humbly to ſue out our Pardon. Then intreaty is of no uſe, but now it may ſteed us; and no requeſt becomes us ſo much, <hi>As Mercy, Lord, in that Day.</hi> If we miſcarry then, we are undone for ever: but if accepted then, we are bleſſed indeed to all <hi>eternity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. The greatneſs of the Bleſſings we expect, which beyond all pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion excel our beſt Endeavours. Eternal Mercy is at the bottom of all God's proceedings with us: Now the leaſt comfort that he beſtows upon us, comes from his Mercy and Grace, and ſhould work a deep ſenſe of it in our Hearts: Gen. 32.10. <hi>I am not worthy of the leaſt of all thy Mercies, and of all thy Truth, which thou haſt ſhewed unto thy Servant.</hi> But then there will be the fulleſt and largeſt manifeſtation of God's Love and Favour to us; 1 Pet. 1.13. <hi>Hope to the end, for the Grace that is to be brought to us at the Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection of Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> There is Grace
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:62862:57"/>brought to us now by the Revelation of Jeſus Chriſt in the Goſpel, in ſome meaſure, but hereafter by that Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation we ſhall ſee his Grace and Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy more fully and perfectly. We ſee his Grace in the pardon of Sins, and that meaſure of Sanctification and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>novation which we attain unto; that he is pleaſed to paſs by our Offences, and to take us into his Family, and give us a taſte of his Love, and a right to the Heavenly Kingdom, and will any way imploy us in his Service. But then it is another manner of Grace and Favour. Indeed, when our Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don and Approbation ſhall be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced and ratified by our Judg's own Mouth, <hi>Acts</hi> 3.17. <hi>Then times of refreſhing ſhall come from the preſence of the Lord.</hi> When he ſhall not only take us into his Family, but into his Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence and Palace, that we may dwell with him for ever; <hi>John</hi> 12.26. Not only give us a Right, but Poſſeſſion. <hi>Matth.</hi> 25.34. Not ſee Chriſt by Faith, but by Sight. 1 <hi>John</hi> 3.2. See our
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:62862:58"/>Perſons admitted into the neareſt frui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of God that may be, and we are capable of. Not only have ſome re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote Service and Miniſtration, but everlaſtingly imployed in loving and delighting in God, and praiſing of God with all thoſe Heavenly Creatures, who are our Eternal Companions in this Work. This is Grace and Mercy indeed. The Grace of God, or his Favour to Sinners, is never ſeen in all its graciouſneſs till then: <hi>Then the praiſe of his glorious Grace doth ſhine forth,</hi> Epheſ. 1.6. <hi>We cry, Grace, Grace</hi> now, when we taſte his Love, but then we have the full and uninterrupted com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion of it. We have much of his Mercy now; <hi>For we are juſtified free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly by his Grace,</hi> Rom. 3.24. <hi>Of his abundant Mercy he hath begotten us to a lively hope,</hi> 1 Pet. 1.3. Grace is as free now as then; but then it is more full. No more trouble with Infirmities or Neceſſities.</p>
            <pb n="111" facs="tcp:62862:58" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>The conſideration of theſe things ſhould preſs us to three things, To be Serious, Humble, and Thankful.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Serious in our preparation for our great Account. The Judgment is ſo exact and impartial, that the choiceſt of God's Servants are fain to refer their whole claim to Mercy. The Bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſs is weighty, we are to be judged to Life or Death, and both are Ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting, we have need to be ſerious in it. The Qualifications are not eaſily to be interpreted, till they evidence and manifeſt themſelves by their power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Influence and multiplied Acts; therefore <hi>we muſt give diligence, that we may be found in him of peace, without ſpot and blameleſs,</hi> 1 Pet. 3.4. Surely you ſhould do all your Works, order all your Actions as Men that ſhall be judged for them, <hi>Jam.</hi> 2.12. <hi>Matth.</hi> 12.36. Conſider what will be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable in the laſt Reckoning, and how things will appear in that Day. I know God's Mercy and Faith in the Blood of Chriſt, will be the chiefeſt
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:62862:59" rendition="simple:additions"/>ground of your Comfort. But you muſt make your Qualification more explicit. A free Pardon through the Mercy of God, and the Merit and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terceſſion of him that redeemed you, is your great Encouragement: but yet you muſt hold on in the way of Holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, that it may ſtead you in your greateſt need. All do not riſe to the Judgment of Abſolution, but ſome to the Judgment of Condemnation; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore you muſt make it evident that you are of the former number, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.1.</p>
            <p n="2">2. To be Humble, by the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg and conſideration of God and your ſelves.</p>
            <p n="1">(1.) Humility becometh us, with reſpect to God. The Throne of Grace is a Throne ſtill; and though we have great liberty and boldneſs by Chriſt, yet we muſt come humbly. There is an everlaſting diſtinction between the Creature and the Creator, and you muſt accordingly addreſs your ſelves: Not as the <hi>Phariſee</hi> that came to chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenge
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:62862:59"/>a Debt, but as the <hi>Publican</hi> that came to emplore Mercy, <hi>Luke</hi> 18.10, 11. He that had a lowly Opinion of himſelf, was moſt acceptable to God.</p>
            <p n="2">(2.) With reſpect to your ſelves. God's Children need to be ſpared in their beſt Actions. Mal. 3.17. <hi>I will ſpare them, as a Man ſpares his own Son that ſerves him.</hi> Nehem. 13.22. <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member me, O my God, concerning this alſo, and ſpare me, according to the greatneſs of thy Mercy.</hi> He ſpeaks this when he had procured God's Ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces to be duly obſerved. He pleadeth no Merit before God, but deſires ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to be ſpared, for he was conſcious of his own many Failings.</p>
            <p n="3">(3.) The ſtrictneſs of your Rule. Pſal. 19.12. <hi>Who can underſtand his Errors? Cleanſe thou me from ſecret Faults.</hi> The Multitude of Errors that we know, and the multitude of them we know not, ſhould keep us hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble.</p>
            <pb n="114" facs="tcp:62862:60"/>
            <p n="3">3. It preſſeth you to Thankfulneſs. From firſt to laſt Mercy ſupplies all our Needs. The Throne of Grace was erected for this purpoſe, that we might have Mercy when we need it moſt. Heb. 4.10. <hi>Let us therefore come boldly unto the Throne of Grace, that we may obtain Mercy, and find Grace to help in a time of need.</hi> All our Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lifications come from Grace; 1 Chron. 29.14. <hi>For all things come of thee.</hi> Luke 19.16. <hi>Not my Induſtry, but thy Pound;</hi> not his own Induſtry, but his Maſters Talent. Gal. 2.20. <hi>Not I, but Chriſt liveth in me; and the life which I now live in the fleſh, I live by the Faith of the Son of God.</hi> 1 Cor. 15.10. <hi>Not I, but the Grace of God which was with me.</hi> Caſt your Crowns of Excellency at the Lambs Feet. <hi>Rev.</hi> 4.10. Let him have all the honour, for you have all from him, and all ſhould be to him. All the Benefits we expect from God, come not for our Righteouſneſs, <hi>Dan.</hi> 9.18. but for this great Mercy. Deut. 9.4, 5.
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:62862:60"/>
               <hi>Say not in thy Heart, for thy Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, the Lord hath brought thee in to poſſeſs the Land.</hi> It is the Mercy of God, that ſets the Crown upon your Heads at laſt.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <p>Page 17, line 14 and 15, for <hi>they,</hi> read <hi>we.</hi> Page 34, line 4, after <hi>mixt,</hi> read <hi>with.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:62862:61"/>
            <head>Some Books printed for, and ſold by <hi>Brab. Aylmer,</hi> at the <hi>3</hi> Pigeons, over againſt the <hi>Royal-Exchange</hi> in Cornhil.</head>
            <p>THe <hi>Harmony of the Divine Attributes,</hi> in the Accompliſhment of Man's Redemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion by the Lord Jeſus Chriſt: Or Diſcourſes, wherein is ſhewed, how the wiſdom, Mercy, Juſtice, Holineſs, Power and Truth of God, are glorified in that great and bleſſed Work: By <hi>William Bates,</hi> D. D. In <hi>Quarto.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Conſiderations of the Exiſtence of God, and of the Immortality of the Soul, with the Recompences of the Future State. To which is now added, the Divinity of the Chriſtian Religion, proved by the Evidence of Reaſon, and Divine Revelation. For the Cure of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidelity, the Hectick Evil of the Times. By <hi>William Bates,</hi> D. D. In <hi>Octavo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Sermons preached upon ſeveral Occaſions, by <hi>Iſaac Barrow,</hi> D. D. late Maſter of <hi>Trinity</hi>-Colledg in <hi>Cambridg,</hi> and one of his Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties Chaplains in Ordinary. In <hi>Octavo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Reconcileableneſs of God's Preſcience of the Sins of Men, with the Wiſdom and Sincerity of his Counſels, Exhortations, and whatſoever means he uſes to prevent them: In a Letter to the Honourable <hi>Rob. Boyl,</hi> 
               <abbr>Eſq</abbr> To which is added a <hi>Poſtſcript</hi> in Defence of the ſaid Letter. By <hi>John How,</hi> M. A. ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time Fellow of <hi>Magdalen</hi>-Colledg. <hi>Oxon.</hi> In <hi>Octavo.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:62862:61"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
